Well, I...I haven't done anything
to deserve this yet, but...
thank you so much.
Let's be frank. There isn't another
person here who could have pulled
this off, hmm?
It was tight,
but we are still in government.
If you're at the table,
you owe this man your job!
Hear, hear!
Well, the good news is that
the country still believes in us.
Obviously, there's a great deal
of work to be done.
Just one word of caution before
we all get our sleeves rolled up.
Briefly.
Tom scored a lot of points in the
election with the way he spoke out
against the excesses
of big business.
No-one would disagree.
But that was electioneering.
This is government.
Meaning?
Meaning...
let's remember who our friends are.
Yes, by all means,
But let's also remember
the people who voted for us.
Don't pull your ear
when you're agitated.
And if your hands are going to shake,
keep them on the podium.
Remember, stay on the road
and don't mention the scenery.
Yes?
What's the latest on the flight
recorder
from Charles Flyte's plane,
Prime Minister?
It hasn't been found.
Surely there's something to report.
It's been three weeks now.
If there was something to tell,
I would tell you.
With respect,
a lot of times government does know
but doesn't tell.
Not this government.
Phrases That Will Come Back
To Haunt Him - number one.
Tweeting, Ros?
Don't you follow me?
The PM's aide, Sayed Khan
- his cousin was released last week.
Does that mean that area
of the investigation is closed?
Sayed Khan was a trusted member of
the late Prime Minister's advisory
team.
So why did he email his cousin
details of Charles Flyte's plane?
He was an aeroplane geek,
and his cousin was, too.
You can scoff, but it's true.
And the doubts
about the plane's safety record?
That model
doesn't have an exemplary record,
but without the black box,
we are in no...
On the black box,
will the Americans be making all
their findings available to you?
Why wouldn't they?
Number two! So soon.
What's happening with Scarrow,
Prime Minister?
You said you're pressing
for the highest compensation.
The HSE report is now imminent.
As you know, I have appointed Lord
Justice Holbeck to chair the public
inquiry.
He's the man. What he says goes.
He says, "Jump," we jump.
And that includes you, too,
by the way, Nightlight.
Will Lord Holbeck be looking
into the circumstances
of the pathologist's death?
Into his suicide? Yes.
The pathologist was
an honourable man
doing a trying job
in difficult circumstances.
The treatment he received was,
in my opinion, quite shameful.
Is it true you spoke to him
the day he died?
Yes.
And I know that there were
toxicology anomalies...
Toxicology anomalies?
When will Lord Holbeck
make his findings available?
Will there be a
statement from the coroner's office?
I'm asking the Lord Justice to look
into them, and why they created
such an impasse
between the company
and the coroner's office.
What about the Scarrow Inquiry?
No more questions.
Thank you for your patience.
Good afternoon.
What happened to "stay on the road
and don't mention the scenery"?
No harm in putting some heat
under the story.
It may focus a few minds
at PetroFex.
Yes, this is Richard Head here.
I'm calling from Lord Holbeck's
team.
'The Scarrow Inquiry?'
'That's right, the inquiry.'
'You may've heard the Prime Minister
'say we'd be looking into the death
of Dr Ashcroft, the pathologist.'
'Awful...'
Oh, yes. Terrible. Erm...
so we're going to need hard copies
of all his emails,
going back six weeks.
'Hard copies. All of them?'
Well, you heard the Prime Minister
say
he wanted a swift resolution
to all this.
'Yes, but hard copies
could take days.'
Well, if you really think it'll take
that long, send them by email.
It'll do for now,
but it's not very satisfactory.
'To what address?'
Er,
richard.head@holbeckinquiry.co.uk.
'Should we cc anyone else?'
No, thank you.
Don't look at me like that.
I'll arrange a statement
regarding the pathologist.
OK.
Do you read Ros Yelland's tweets?
Do I look like somebody
who reads tweets?
Maybe you should start.
Paul Clark. Try him again.
Track him down.
Two words - coal minister.
OK.
Hello.
So did he kill himself?
It would seem so.
And do you believe that?
Yes.
Congratulations, by the way.
Does your ascendancy mean I now have
an inside man at Number 10?
I recall you telling me
it wasn't going to happen.
And you telling me not to believe
what I read in the papers.
And what are we going to read
in the papers?
Since we're getting on so famously,
I've been told I can do a profile.
Your first 30 days.
Really?
Really.
Is this you?
You've been doing your research.
It's Bosnia in 1992.
And you were where else?
Ulster. Germany.
That's you and...?
Look, have we got time to talk?
No, I'm afraid we don't.
I've got a very important meeting
with the Indian Minister for Coal.
It's a shame.
Please, go ahead.
I have wet wipes here.
Let's get our hands dirty.
This coal provided
the underground boiler room
that made this nation what it is
today.
And yet, what do you say to us?
Leave our coal where it is.
The planet can't take it.
"You've reached Tom Dawkins.
Leave a message..."
Oh, that's right. You ignore me, too.
The dark patches are burn marks.
In all probability, a bomb.
But they were passing through
an electrical storm,
and until we can rule out
a lightning strike...
...my advice would be
to say nothing.
Jesus.
Poor bastards.
Spike Ellis Kane.
Why?
Too close to the PM.
Anthony Fossett's close to the PM.
How come we don't delete him?
Sir...
Problem, Sergeant?
Oh, Jesus Christ.
It's Lord Snooty.
Hello, Tony.
You didn't answer my calls!
Have you seen my schedule for today?
So you're busy. Don't carp.
Some of us aren't. What...
What do you think of your boss, guys?
I say he's a fucking cock who
doesn't remember who his friends are.
Don't...
You don't say much, do you?
Can we talk freely?
I think you already have.
Dermot Matthews was dying
before he was killed
in the Scarrow explosion.
Dermot...?
You found his daughter's hand.
His immune system was totally fucked.
The problem is,
the trigger word is Nightlight.
Whenever he says Nightlight,
I'm supposed to monitor.
So?
But his cat's called Nightlight.
Nightlight was an MI5/Special Branch
operation in Northern Ireland
in the '80s.
We are a listening station, Agnes.
That's all.
Matthews worked at PetroFex,
which his GP thinks was significant,
as does the pathologist.
There's mention of a substance. Um...
It's...
..PFX-44.
They won't spike Tony Fossett
because he's an intramural subject.
Meaning?
Special request
by someone senior in Intelligence.
Laura, what an...
what an unexpected pleasure.
The sergeant will take you home now,
Tony.
The night is young.
The Prime Minister's car
is waiting for him.
Then perhaps you and I could go
and find somewhere quiet
and talk about old times.
You're not cleared to be here, Tony.
And you're drunk.
I am not drunk. Huh?
I'm not falling down, am I?
I'm not... I'm not...stotious,
as they say in the Six Counties.
Do you remember them?
Oh, this is great, isn't it?
Three Westminster panjandrums
enjoying each other's company
at the fulcrum of imperial power.
Cigar, anyone?
Ah-ha-ha...!
Come on, sir. Time to go.
Another time.
I'll hold you to that.
Hey...!
It's personal.
I embarrassed you, Tom. Sorry.
No, Tony, it's OK.
We were both going places once,
weren't we?
You got over your...bump in the road.
Nightlight! Here, puss.
I never got over mine.
You will, Tony.
You will.
Come here.
How about a quick one
down the Drum and Monkey
before it's feeding time for you
penguins?
I can't. Really, I can't.
Yeah, you can.
You're the Prime Minister.
Gotta go, Tony.
What, gonna let Nanny tell you
who you can and can't play with?
A bad influence, am I? Is that it?
Know too much about you, do I?
Good night, Tony.
Not allowed on little Tommy's
trampoline?
Morning, Laura.
Does Sergeant Wrigglesworth
not encourage you to jog
somewhere different every time?
Yes, he does.Hmm.
So...do you have anything
on the black box for me?
Or should I...should I ask
Tony Fossett?
The tabloids' favourite
phone hacker?
Well, the man had to eat.
And you were the one who put him
out of a job at MI5.
He said that you sacked him
to cover up your own mistakes.
Did he?
And does he think it's funny
bandying that stuff about
when he's aware there's people
who'll twist it against me?
You saw him. He's unstable.
No. Nothing on the black box.
Al-Qaeda claimed it pretty early on,
but then again, they would.
Their Arabian Peninsula man,
al-Gamdi, has form
with aircraft bombs,
and we know he's in Afghanistan.
Which is a long way
out of his comfort zone.
So something's up.
We all have a past, Tom.
Why do you think he was
on the plane?
Everybody else in the picture
got on the plane. Count them.
So what's he doing there?
Walking past, that's what it looks
like to me. Who knows?
And this one?
That's one of the pilots.
Look at his shirt.
Both the pilots are there.
How long have you spent on this?
I've only been doing it
in my spare time.
The Prime Minister died on that
flight.
Shouldn't we be exploring
every possible angle?
You're beyond your remit.
I'm bored of my remit.
That's why you showed me those.
Then I'll take it from here.
I want my contribution credited.
If you want stars on your badge,
go and work for McDonald's.
The pathologist's request
for information.
Now, I'm not going to tell you your
job, Prime Minister, but I can't see
why you want to set me up
as the head of a very expensive
public inquiry team
if you're going to dish out surmise
and half-truth to the Fourth Estate
before I've got my feet
under the desk.
Well, I'm not going to tell you
your job, Lord Holbeck,
but the country's demanding answers.
HSE is dragging its feet.
The company is dragging its feet.
Paul Clark is incommunicado.
And the compensation
is nowhere in sight.
Now...
PFX-44.
Do they say what that is?
No. The PetroFex take on it
seems to be that the toxins
are an unnecessary distraction.
They maintain that it's dirty tricks
by green activists, or sabotage.
And have you seen anything
that might back that up?
About the only thing
we have managed to ascertain
is that the shockwave travelled
a great deal further
than the existing worst-case
scenarios.
The initial explosion seems
to have been aggravated by a second.
When I hear more, I'll let you know.
Thank you.
General Munnery wants a word
before Prime Minister's Questions.
He says it's urgent.
Peter, would you put the sound up,
please?
Responding to a question about
the lack of progress
with the PetroFex compensation deal
for Scarrow,
Mrs Yelland is said to have remarked
that there are some politicians
who take very naturally
to leadership,
and others who need time
to find their range.
No need to read tweets now,
is there?
I'm going to put a clock
on PetroFex.
They have until midday tomorrow.
Tell them I expect them
to provide the coroner
with everything
the former pathologist requested.
And tell them I'll be addressing
the nation on the issue.
Have you spoken to Paul Clark?
Not yet, no.
Call him. Tell him as well.
It's the middle of the night
where he is.
Wake the bastard.
Afghanistan. Al-Qaeda's number three,
al-Gamdi, is on the move.
Footage from an unarmed drone,
one of ours, taken yesterday.
Was he aware he was spotted?
No evidence for that,
Foreign Secretary.
And where is he now?
Holed up near Lashkar Gah.
We're pretty sure he's making
for Yemen, via Oman,
so he may be planning
to pass through Pakistan here.
If we're going to get a shot at him,
it'll have to be before that.
Mm. And what do the Americans say?
Well, given their grandstanding
over the search
for the black box, I...
You haven't told them.
Not so as they'd notice.
And do you think they'd notice
if one of our submarines
took a bit of a poke around
for the black box?
Military men like ourselves,
Prime Minister,
we'd make a better fist
of running this country
than all the politicians
put together.
I think it's the fist part
that worries people, General.
Keep me informed.
Ros, walk with me.
It was supposed to be off
the record.
You know, Ros,
when I took over the leadership,
my first thought was to return you
very swiftly to the back benches.
Do you know who advised me
not to do that?
No, but you're going to tell me.
Nobody.
I'd like to know
the Prime Minister's thoughts
on his Foreign Secretary's comments.
Is she right in saying
that he's "yet to find his range"?
Or were her words perhaps taken
out of context?
I think the Right Honourable Member
has just answered her own question.
Does the Prime Minister at least
agree that PetroFex
is playing him for a fool...
...by refusing to provide
the coroner with information,
despite the Prime Minister's
much-publicised ultimatum?
Is the Prime Minister aware
of any response at all?
Perhaps the Right Honourable Member
will care to ask me in...
22 hours.
You want to be careful.
I don't actually, Felix.
I want to be noticed.
And when he comes a cropper,
I want people to say,
"Remember what Ros Yelland said?"
Have you seen his approval figures?
There'll be a wobble, one day.
Wait and see.
And maybe we'll have a proper
leadership election
instead of a coronation.
And then...who knows?
People like him.
The people like him.
Did he consult you about whether
to keep me in the Cabinet, Felix?
Well, he might have
talked about it briefly.
And you said what?
I said, "Absolutely.
Of course you should."
A potential leader like yourself...
General Munnery.
Says it's time to make a fist.
I think you know everyone -
Special Ops, MI5, MI6.
So this is our...our man, al-Gamdi.
Just need to get our angles right.
And get the word from you,
Prime Minister.
You're sure it's him?
We're as sure as we ever could be.
Er, we've not met, Prime Minister.
Not face to face.
William Hawley, MI6.
I'm not sure that we have,
in this light.
I do my best work in the dark.
Laura here prefers
a little more light.
You're wasting time.
If he crosses into Iran...
You may remember
his signature piece was that...
I don't need to be softened up.
I'm quite well aware that he's
a cold-hearted killer, thank you.
Of course. Forgetting you were
an Army man yourself.
Things have changed a bit
since then.
You get to stand a lot farther back
from the action, you mean.
It doesn't leave you, does it,
Prime Minister? Being in the field.
No, it doesn't.
Double back.
They're on to us.
We need to strike now. If they
split up and make a run for it,
we'll never get him.
Prime Minister...
Prime Minister,
we need to strike now.
this may be our one shot.
Passenger side. That'll be al-Gamdi.
Tom, for Christ's sake!
They've seen us.
They're taking cover.
Prime Minister...
Tom.
They're praying.
Well, then, we've got him.
We can't kill a man
while he's praying.
It's the best time to go,
when your stock's high
with your maker.
There's only one thing
watching over those guys from above,
and you won't find it in the Qur'an.
If we're going to act like gods,
can we at least maintain
the demeanour?
They're heading back to the vehicle.
Tom!
Prime Minister,
we're running out of time.
They're on the move.
This is our last chance.
Go.
Affirmative.
Got him!
Pick that out!
Congratulations, Prime Minister.
You killed a very bad man today.
I think a drink is called for.
I've just heard from
the crash investigation team.
They have ruled out
the lightning strike.
Was it a bomb?
Do you have any suspects?
You've just atomised
the most likely one.
Are the Americans going
to announce it?
No.
Then we have to.
It's going to leak out.
They want to do more analysis.
I don't want them doing anything
unless they inform us first.
Laura...
Those people
who might twist things against you.
Was one of them...?
Blooded now, Prime Minister?
One of us?
Hello?Piers?
Don't say my name.
Do you know who this is?
'Can you say some more?'
You gave me a reference for a job.
'Oh, yes.'
I was hoping we could...
..have a talk.
My advice
is to drop the PetroFex deadline.
You've got great headlines
on the al-Gamdi strike,
but you could lose all the benefit
of that if they defy you.
Bask in the glory while you can.
Unequivocal good news.
Not according to the US State
Department.
They're pissed off
they didn't get him, that's all.
Please.
Gina, if they meet my deadline,
I win.
If they don't,
they give me licence
to go after them twice as hard.
Thank you.
Of course, this doesn't mark
the end to the fight against terror.
There are still sinister forces
at work in our country
determined to disrupt
the process of democracy.
And I understand that there may be
some of you who have questions
about the action taken.
But be assured of this.
That because of British Intelligence
and British technology,
a terrorist responsible for
the deaths of thousands of people
has been stopped.
I think he just added "Churchillian"
to his positive points of reference.
Watch the clock.
And finally this is Madeline
Wolstencroft and Keith Thompson
from the Evening Globe.
Thank you so much for coming.
The deadline is in a few minutes.
Yes, I know, Gina. Thank you.
If you need
any further information...
Feel good to have your Army hat
back on again?
Everything clear-cut.
Good guys, bad guys.
You think I'm that uncomplicated?
No.
No. Your Press Officer,
on the other hand,
looks like she's growing
an ulcer very fast.
She's concerned about the deadline.
And you're not?
I was talking to a friend
the other day
and I was telling him
that I couldn't do something,
and he said, "Oh, yes, you can.
"You are the Prime Minister."
Maybe he's right.
Yeah.
While we're in Cloud Cuckoo Land,
when are we going to do this profile?
I'm afraid I have to hurry you
along, Ellis.
What is that?
Oh, that's just scraps
of my Tom Dawkins jigsaw.
I dig deep, by the way.
It's a rules of engagement card,
for Bosnia.
Yeah. I like to know the rules
of engagement.
Oh, a minute to, by the way.
Any news?
No.
So, go on.
You told your line manager.
He's always trying to find ways
of talking to me.
I think he thinks that this is
just another way he can...
And I don't want to go
above his head,
because we have to work together.
But I've seen something
in these photos.
I mean, it's all probably nothing...
Go on.
You recruited me, Piers.
And I thought if I told you, you
would... tell me what you thought.
Just a moment.
Agnes,
this is William Hawley, MI6.
Agnes is feeling a bit unloved,
William.
Ah, yes. Chilly place, Cheltenham,
Agnes. I've always said it.
William's very interested
in your findings.
Oh, rest assured, Miss Evans,
they're finding traction
in very high places,
and your name with them. All right?
You've already seen them?
We'll let the matter rest there
for now, shall we?
Let us take it from here.
Tony Fossett.
What about him?
I think MI5 might... Laura Duchenne
seems to have it in for him,
and I don't think it's right.
He's very close to the PM,
and perhaps
we shouldn't be monitoring him.
Don't worry, Agnes.
We know all about Tony Fossett.
Confusion in Whitehall
as the Prime Minister's deadline
comes and goes
with no response from PetroFex
bosses.
Oil tanker drivers
say they will take action
if fuel prices continue to rise.
Also this lunchtime,
youth unemployment
reaches a record high,
and an al-Qaeda...
What the fuck are they playing at?
Politics, I guess.
Want me to prepare a statement?
Yes, please.
Paul Clark, sir.
A friend of mine works at airports.
Apparently,
Clark's en route to Davos.
Anywhere but here!
Not quite, sir. He's stopping
to refuel at Biggin Hill.
We've held him as you requested,
but he's refusing to leave the
plane.
What if I go to him?
That would make me nervous,
Prime Minister.
Sergeant?
I could do with
stretching my legs, sir.
You don't suppose they'll shoot us,
do you, Sergeant?
You can never tell with
the Americans, sir.
Prime Minister, I'm going to ask you
to stop right there.
Is the man with you armed?
I should bloody well hope so.
I suggest you step down.
Thank you.
Tom!
What can I do for you?
Apart from sue you, of course.
My lawyers are on it as we speak.
They'll find something.
They're in touch with the US
Attorney General as well, by the way.
I want to know what PFX-44 is.
And I want to know
what happened to Dermot Matthews.
I signed a legal contract
with the British Government
to develop that site.
I provided 1,600 jobs that would
otherwise have gone to Poland.
I gave Dermot Matthews the first job
he or anyone in his family
had even heard of for a generation.
And what do I get for it?
Your company made billions
from that site.
And may I remind you that there are
19 people dead and 94 injured.
The people of Scarrow want to know
that you are going to pay up
and stay put.
You want us to make good
with the people of Scarrow,
cut out the red tape
and the deadlines...
..and the public inquiries.
You set up in this country,
you abide by its rules.
The oil majors
could buy and sell this country.
And you with it.
Be grateful we pay lip service.
What's PFX-44?
It's a new lightweight drone fuel
we're developing at Scarrow.
It's more jobs for your precious
country, more firepower.
Or, if you prefer, we can take
the whole thing to Poland.
Now, shall we drop it?
Charles Flyte did.
Who else knew?
Well, I'd love to tell you,
but unfortunately
your Chief of Defence Staff
made me sign a bit of paper
saying I wouldn't.
There's no evidence
that the drone fuel
caused or exacerbated
the disaster.
Do you actually believe that,
General?
Or are you just able to get your
mouth to form the words regardless?
A little respect, please,
Prime Minister.
I could remind you that you never
rose above the rank of captain.
And which electorate voted you
Chief of Defence Staff?
It was felt that any adverse
publicity to do with the drone fleet
might jeopardise the kill.
Which kill was that? Al-Gamdi
or the 19 people dead in Scarrow?
I want a list of everyone who knew.
Think of the long term.
Think of the lives saved
just 24 hours ago
with the drone strike you ordered.
Using the new drone fuel.
Was that an attempt to embroil me
in this conspiracy?
It's not as if it's your first,
Prime Minister.
I hope to God that you've held on
to your body armour, General.
Cos you're going to need it.
You're forgetting
the Official Secrets Act.
And you're presuming
your secret's official.
Nills.
Paul.
Dermot Matthews.
At the refinery gate.
So?
It's moments before the explosion.
And he wasn't on shift.
'As my deadline with the
company expired at noon today,
'I learned that a group of people
within the PetroFex Corporation
'have been working in secret
'to develop a fuel
for use in unmanned drones,
'like the ones responsible
for killing Tamin al-Gamdi.'
None of us will shed a tear
for a mass murderer like al-Gamdi,
but it's my belief
that the experimental fuel
may well be responsible
for the scale and ferocity
of the Scarrow explosion
and for the toxicity anomalies
I mentioned
in my press conference
a few days ago.
When one of the largest oil
companies in the world flouts
our nation's safety regulations
and the terms of the company's
agreement with the UK government,
I believe that we have to act,
and act together as a nation.
You know,
I was told today
that the oil majors
could buy and sell this country.
Petrodollars are a powerful
currency, there's no doubt.
But we hold a stronger one
in our democracy.
We call it the vote.
Tom...I'm sorry to disturb you.
That drone strike.
The Iranians say
it was on their side of the border.
They're treating it as an act of war.
We have not committed any act of war
against Iran.
There's...a small possibility that
the missile crossed the border.
PetroFex is said to be on the verge
of relocating to Poland.
They've suspended their offer
of compensation.
I'm gonna freeze
their fucking assets.
It's a good story,
but I can get you a better one.
Tom Dawkins: The Army Years.
This is your chance, Tom.
There is no story.
Sir, the biometric database
has been compromised.
Who is it?
His name's Sami Shiroor.
He was on the plane
with Charles Flyte.
He may have been working
for the Iranians.