Hey, everyone Dr. Z,
welcome to The ZDoggMD Show.
Today I have a special guest
look, I moved back to the Bay Area,
so I could talk to smart people
at places like UCSF and
Stanford and in the Bay area.
And I was all excited and then COVID hit
and it was Zoom, Zoom,
Zoom, and I hate Zoom.
So today I have someone
I've been wanting to talk to
since this pandemic started,
Dr. Jay Bhattacharya is a
Stanford Professor of Medicine
and he has training and
specialty in economics.
Actually tell me Jay
Jay, who are you man?
- Well, okay.
- Not in a metaphysical sense.
- Exactly, so I am a Professor
of Medicine as you said
at Stanford university,
I've been at Stanford on the
faculty for about 20 years.
I've an MD and a PhD in Economics.
And I studied health policy
and health economics.
I've been working on infectious disease,
economics and epidemiology
for 20 some years now.
- So the reason I wanted
to have you on the show
was what you just said.
You have the MD Stanford
training and PhD in economics,
which means you can see in a way
that many frontline healthcare people,
including public health people,
aren't able to see the bigger picture.
Now you came to prominence
during the pandemic
as one of the coauthors
of the Stanford Seroprevalence Study,
which raised all kinds of interesting.
I mean, tell me about that experience
because I was talking
about your piece early on
saying, hey, this is true.
The actual infection
fatality rate of this disease
is actually much lower than we thought
it's still higher than flu,
but it's not as high as
they've been saying in China.
What was that experience like?
- I mean, that was incredible.
Just an amazing, in
some ways, dispiriting,
but also exciting experience.
Let me kind of go back just a little bit?
- [Dr. Z] Absolutely.
- So what got me into it
was I had done some work
during the H1N1 Flu epidemic in 2009.
- [Dr. Z] I remember that one.
- I mean, it was a big
deal at the time, right?
But luckily it didn't turn
out to be as bad as COVID,
but especially at the beginning,
people were really, really panicked
over the high fatality rates
that were the case fatality rates
that were coming up out
of all around the world.
- I remember I was a practicing
hospitalist at Stanford
and everybody was like,
we're all going to die.
It was a kind of a catastrophization.
- Yeah, it's actually
an in the early days,
there was good reason.
There were these case fatality rates
that looked like Ebola.
It just did look terrible.
In the months that followed
what happened was people
did zero prevalence studies
and found that
there were many times
more cases of infections
than there had been cases in H1N1
and the infection fatality rate,
which turned out to be
about a hundred times less
than the initial case fatality
rates in the H1N1 case.
- So let me reiterate that for people
who don't understand
some of the terminology.
So case fatality rate is when someone
is actually tested for
disease, presents to care
and is diagnosed with the disease,
and then how many people
die out of that group.
- [Dr. Jay] Correct.
- Infection fatality rate
is, well, of all the
infections that exist,
including ones that we weren't
able to openly diagnose.
What's the rate of fatality in that group.
And it was 100X different in H1N1.
- [Dr. Jay] In H1N1 that's right.
- And so this got you interested then
when COVID came around, I imagine.
- It looked like a repeat to me, right?
So looked like the people were finding
enormously high case fatality rates.
I think World Health
Organization said 3.4%.
There was a piece published
in JAMA in February
Journal of American Medical
Association, that said 2.2%.
And these are terrible numbers.
- These are horrifying numbers.
These are the kind of
numbers that would cause you
to lock down the entire planet instantly,
because you're gonna lose
that percentage of your population
if everybody gets infected.
- Millions and millions
of people dead, right
if that's the number in
the United States alone.
- [Dr. Z] Alone.
- If the numbers are right.
But that was what happened at H1N1.
And I said okay, well, do we really know
how many people actually have it?
And at the same time we're worried
about how much testing resources we had.
Remember there was a shortage of tests.
So we're just holding onto the test
to look at people who
actually have serious disease,
which is what you ought to do
from a clinical perspective.
But then from an
epidemiologic perspective,
can you extrapolate that
to say, okay the population at large
3% of us are all gonna die if we get it.
And we don't have the answer to that.
So that's what led to the
Stanford Seroprevalence Study.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- And the other share problem
studies I've worked on.
So it was this hypothesis.
Like how many people actually have it?
How deadly actually is it?
- And so how did you do this study?
Because there was a ton of
controversy around the methods
and the actual sensitivity specificity
of the assay that you use and all that.
- Yeah, so that was a lot
of confusion around that.
So we wanted to do a study
that could be done very, very quickly,
put it in the field very, very quickly.
At the time of the study
the FDA had approved for use
some, the lateral flow assays,
they looked like pregnancy tests,
like little pregnancy kits.
The one we used had pretty
good error properties.
You know every medical test has errors.
I mean, there's just not a,
and you can't avoid that.
That's just the nature of,
we don't have a tri-corder
that can automatically tell me exactly
what's wrong with you, right?
We need to look at the
numbers and interpret them.
At the time the FDA had approved for use
these little lateral assayed tests,
including the one we use, for sale
but they hadn't approved them
for general use in the population.
We could use them for research purposes,
but not for clinical purposes.
So we use one of those, the
reason it was very simple.
There are two kinds of tests
to do antibody testing,
there's these ELISA tests,
which are pretty accurate
and then these lateral flow assay tests.
For the ELISA's, you have
to draw venous blood.
It's really hard in the
middle of a pandemic
to go out and find,
you know, can I draw
venous blood from you?
A big vial of it,
or I can just do a little finger stick.
The nice thing about epidemiologic work
is that you can correct for the errors,
which is what we did.
Actually I've run three
Seroprevalence Studies,
one in Santa Clara
County, one in LA County,
and one in with Major League Baseball.
- Did you get to meet a
lot of baseball players?
- I got to meet a lot
of, not baseball players,
I mean it was surreal,
I got to be in a meeting
with all the owners.
It was just--
- [Dr. Z] Oh, wow, that's nice.
- It was fantastic.
I had to contain myself when
I met the Yankee's owner,
but, you know, that's another thing.
So I ran three different studies
and the interesting
thing about the studies
was we use very different methods
to try to disseminate them.
So the Santa Clara
Study was the first one.
It was a big study, 2000
some people in the Bay area
in Santa Clara County.
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- We wrote the study very
quickly and we released it
through an open science process,
- Like a pre print,
- A pre print, right, exactly.
So now the traditional path
involves sending it to a journal.
The journal then sends it to
three anonymous reviewers.
No one will hear it about it, except me.
And that's how I spend
my life dealing with this
three anonymous reviews,
all of them always hate me.
- So you're not used to the
whole planet hating you at once.
- Yeah, that was interesting.
So we sent it and I got 10,000
peer reviews in one day.
- [Dr. Z] Oh my gosh.
- And it was kind of
interesting, exciting.
I learned a lot.
So we made, what I would characterize
a relatively minor error in
standard error calculation,
which we corrected within a week.
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- And the number that we
got was absolutely stunning.
What we found was that the disease
was 50 times more prevalent
than people thought based
on just the case number.
So people thought in Santa Clara County,
there were a 1000 cases as of April 3rd,
I think it was.
But in fact based on the study,
you could tell 50,000 people
had, had some antibody
evidence of it the same time.
- Right, which would correspond
to an infection fatality rate
at that time of what?
- About two in 1,000.
- [Dr. Z] two in a 1,000
- So that means
out of the 1,000 people
who got the infection, 998 survived.
- So 0.2%.
- 0.2%.
- So double what we think
the mortality is for flu.
- Well I am not 100% sure I
know what the flu mortality,
I know the evidence, it's unclear in flu
no one's done the same
kind of infection fatality rate numbers
that they've done with for COVID
that they've dealt with the flu.
- So in many ways we're
comparing apples to oranges
when we're comparing flu--
- So let's come back
to that flu comparison.
'Cause it is interesting and important,
but I think the key thing
is how much would you change your life '
for two in a 1,000 risk?
And there's a couple
other things we learned.
So one is that if you're
older, it's much higher.
It's probably much worse
than the flu actually.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- For older
- Order of magnitude.
- So if you're over 70
versus if you're let's say
you're under 15 or under 10.
It's on the order of a
1000 to one difference
in mortality probability.
So the flu is much more
deadly if you're older,
if you're over let's say 65 or 70.
And if you're under--
- The flu or COVID we are talking about?
- I'm sorry COVID I apologize.
It's COVID is much more deadly
if you're over 65 or 70,
and if you're under say
40, the flu is worse.
That's what seroprevalence studies shows.
- And that was the sense that
I was getting early on too.
And seroprevalence study
was supporting that.
And you said something which
we're gonna get back to.
I think that's a theme of this,
how much would you change your life
for a two in a 1000 chance, right?
- Yeah and I think that age
difference is important.
The absolute number is also important
well, let's get back to that theme.
- Yeah , absolute versus
relative risk, yeah.
- So the interesting thing about that,
so we released the LA County Study.
It was immediately accepted
in JAMA and published.
- Just instant.
- It's the same number
- Peer reviewed.
- Peer reviewed, yeah.
I've never had such an
easy time with a review
it was a very strange.
Whereas the Santa Clara
Study, it exploded Twitter.
I'm not on Twitter myself.
- Thank God for you.
- It was actually probably
good for my sanity.
- It really is.
- And everyone on earth
was paying attention to it
all at once, one study, right.
- [Dr. Z] Right, pre print.
- And everyone was convinced
that I was absolutely wrong.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- 100% wrong because people
had fixed in their mind,
New York City where the
death rate was higher.
Actually we know from
seroprevalence studies
that it was higher,
the actual infection fatality rate
was higher in New York City.
So now since then 50 some studies
from around the world have been done.
And there's a consistent theme
that the infection fatality rates
somewhere between two and three in 1,000,
just like what we found in Santa Clara,
just like what we found in LA County
and the places that have higher density
where you think did worse,
you know, Bergamot, New
York City, they did worse.
Their infection fatality rate is worse
five in a 1,000, six in a 1,000
in some Spain, maybe 10 in a 1,000.
- So, okay, there's a lot here.
And again, this gets me fired up
because I've been talking
about this myself,
why would an infection
fatality rate be different
in say New York versus at Santa Clara?
Walk me through that.
- Yeah, sure so we think
about infection fatality rate
as if it were just a--
- [Dr. Z] Static.
- Well, as if it's the virus itself,
it's a feature of the virus.
Here's the virus.
Here's the infection fatality rate.
That's wrong thinking.
It's a function of the virus obviously,
the biology of the virus,
but also the host
and also of the healthcare system
taking care of the patient.
- Do they survive or do they care
- All three of those things matter a ton.
- [Dr. Z] Ah.
- So for instance,
if you look at the case
fatality rate for this disease,
just case fatality forget about
infection fatality, right?
This is the number of
people who have the disease
who actually died from it.
It's declined very sharply
since March and April.
- Sure has, cases up deaths down.
- Has the virus changed?
Maybe a little, I mean,
there's some mutation,
but not enough to think
that it's had any appreciable change.
What it is, is a few things.
One is the set of people
that are getting infected
are less vulnerable to it.
They tend to be younger.
And so they just don't die
at higher rates from it.
The second we were better at managing it,
better treating it.
- Right, dexamethasone.
- [Dr. Jay] Exactly.
- Not intubating everyone.
- Not killing people
with ventilators right.
I mean that would seem
like a really good idea.
- Yeah which by the way,
wasn't clear in the beginning at all.
So not to disparage people
who are intubating everyone,
but we just didn't know.
- Yeah, I know, look, I
have a lot of sympathy
and people were really brave going in
when we didn't have the numbers.
I honor that, absolutely.
But it is absolutely the case,
we've learned a lot about
how to treat the disease
and we're much better at
managing than we once we're.
I think that kind of news
ought to get out more.
That seems like an important fact,
our understanding of
disease shouldn't be frozen
in Amber, in March.
- No, so you're appreciated the choir
because I just did a video on this,
on the cases up deaths down.
I actually think that there is a lot
of catastrophization and misunderstanding,
and there's been a polarity
that I've not seen in science ever.
And the thing is folks like you,
this is the thing I
criticized your trial as well,
but also put it out there
and said, hey, this is what's going on.
This is the critique, et cetera.
- Well, science, that's how it works.
- That's what you do in science.
- I mean, I didn't mind the science.
of course we talk,
we look at the data,
we try to interpret it.
That's the fun part of science.
- But the vitriol and the censorship too,
like Ioniddis is your partner in that
one of the most respected scientists
actually has done papers
and papers and papers
on how we get science wrong
with our own biases, right.
Was accused of severe bias and censored.
- Yeah, it was absolutely shocking.
So, like Buzzfeed attack
my family, Buzzfeed.
- Can I say, so anytime I
see anything in Buzzfeed,
if it isn't 10 reasons
celebrities have done something
that make you go, what I'm shook!
I don't listen to it because
it's so clearly biased.
- Yeah, it was really kind of
- Buzzfeed attacked your family?
- Yeah they said my wife was involved
in like she volunteered,
my daughter actually volunteered as a,
it was lot of community involvement
with the feeling around
the study in Santa Clara
was a lot of volunteers
a lot of people,
it was a really good feeling.
And my wife was super
excited about the study.
She's an oncologist.
She wrote a email and to her friends,
encouraging them to sign up
and somebody leaked the email,
which had some information
that was not quite right.
And then Buzzfeed made
her international news.
- [Dr. Z] Oh my God.
- That's the hardest part of this.
It was just getting my
family involved with it
in a way that I didn't expect.
- What's the agenda for that,
that you're somehow
minimizing the pandemic
and gonna cost lives, is that right?
- I think so, that's part of it.
The same Buzzfeed author
then wrote an accusation
that somehow, because people gave money,
including like, I guess
a JetBlue executive
- Right, I saw that.
- [Dr. Jay] To Stanford
- Right, right 5000 bucks.
- [Dr. Jay] 5,000,
- So 5000 which is a rounding
error on the cost of a trial.
- Well, in this case, the study was
we ran a really cheap,
it was less than a $100,000 for the study.
- [Dr. Z] Nice.
- But they give the money to Stanford
and somehow I'm gonna
change the results for the,
it's just ridiculous.
- You know what,
Jay, when you're in big JetBlue's pocket
anything goes wrong
- It was really kind of him
to give money for thE study
was like, I'm grateful.
- And that's fine that
he had his own agenda,
which was probably, hey, yeah.
- Everyone has an agenda
- [Dr. Z] Everyone has an agenda.
- So my agenda was to
learn what that number was.
I think we now know it.
- So your feeling now is that somewhere
between 0.2 and 0.3%
infection fatality rates.
- That's the median around the world
- Median, around the world,
It may be higher in
places like a New York.
- [Dr. Jay] Yeah.
- Why was it higher in
New York, do you think?
- I think there's lots of reasons.
I think potential one is
I think the set of people
that were infected in New York were older.
And the institutions
where they are infected
was less capable of dealing with it
in the early days of the epidemic.
So there's something to this
and the fact that it was older people
in nursing home settings
that weren't sort of
equipped to manage it.
I think that played a big role
in why it was higher in New York.
The other thing is I think there's a,
and this is a theory I've seen,
I think, I mean, there's something to it,
when viral load is higher,
when you're exposed to it
multiple times over and over again,
you just get a worse outcome.
So I talked about this with
Monica Gandhi yesterday
on the show UCSF ID doc,
and her theory of viral inoculum
correlating to severity.
- I saw that.
- Yeah, yeah and she actually posited
the same exact thing in,
it's a theory like it's
was hypothesis in New York
was that people are in
the built environment
or on top of each other,
especially minority communities,
which were hardest hit.
And so, as a result, if you're
out in Queens or somewhere,
and you're just living
in this multifamily home,
told to stay in doors, right.
What are you doing?
You get a high viral inoculum.
And again, it's a hypothesis,
but it's interesting
because that would affect
your infection fatality ratio
if that is a component of
how severely ill you get.
- Correct and that is what explains
why nosocomial spreads
like hospital's spread
it's so important.
- Exactly.
We talked Dr. Li, the guy,
the ophthalmologist in Wuhan
who first sort of broke this
news and he died and he was 33
and the thought was,
he's an ophthalmologist.
So he's seeing patients
this close to their face,
getting viral inoculum right in the face.
And now we've learned a lot from that.
that's why we in N95 and
face shield in the hospital
and paper and all that.
If we can yeah.
So do you think the
infection fatality ratio,
if you just looked at one community,
like say Latinos, Latinas,
would you think it'd be higher
there from what we're seeing?
- From what I've seen,
I think that minorities are
harder hit with this epidemic.
That's absolutely true.
So black communities, Latino
communities are been harder,
especially in California,
Latino communities make
up the bulk of the--
- Disease yeah, 45% yeah.
- It's incredible, I don't think
the infection fatality rates,
- Sorry 60%,
60% of cases in California
- But I don't think that
the infection fatality rate
is much higher conditional on getting it.
It's just they're more likely to get it.
- [Dr. Z] I see.
- It may be a little higher.
I mean, you know, it's hard to.
- See because is there preexisting disease
more in that community,
chronic disease, diabetes,
hypertension disease.
- Yeah, that's the question.
So if you have these
underlying conditions,
of course, you're more likely to die from,
if you're older you're
more likely to die from it,
things like that we know for a fact.
Once you control for that,
if you're Hispanic, are
you more likely to die?
My guess is probably not.
- [Dr. Z] Interesting.
- It's mostly those preexisting conditions
and the fact that you're
more likely get it
in the first place.
- Now, one counter proposal
I might say as well,
if viral inoculum does matter,
if that hypothesis is true
and Hispanic families are more likely
to congregate together under one roof,
you might see
actually a higher infection
fatality rate in that.
- It could be yeah.
There's a study that was done in Mumbai,
in the Dharavi Slums in Mumbai.
- Yes, I saw that, explain it.
- First, the, the prevalence was enormous.
I mean, I think it was like--
- It was 80%, 60 or 80.
- I actually talked to some
of those study authors,
the studies who ran the thing.
Essentially the idea they have
is that the lockdown put people,
this is a slum where like 10
people live in the same house
and there's police walking around,
making sure that if you
walk out of the house,
you're gonna be arrested.
So they put 10 people in the house,
they probably spread the
disease with the lockdown,
enormous viral load.
You can see with the 80%
antibody number right.
- Right
- But the infection fatality
rate was really low.
- Minuscule.
- [Dr.  Jay] Yeah.
- Like I think it might
be an under reporting
to some degree, but like 200,
300 deaths out of all these.
- Yeah it was really, really low.
So part of that is they
don't have the diabetes,
they don't have the obesity,
they don't have those kinds
of predisposing conditions.
- 'Cause they're thin.
- [Dr. Jay] And they're younger.
- They're younger.
- So, I think we're still learning
and at least I'm still
learning quite a lot
about this disease.
- Well, and you know the
other thought that I had,
and again, this is just
pure mental masturbation
is the idea that that group may be exposed
to so many pathogens on a daily basis,
including Corona Viruses, et cetera,
that they have some innate
T-cell immunity or mucosal immune
something that we don't have.
- Yeah, I think there's some evidence
of that even in the United States right.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah, exactly.
- I saw this really interesting
study where it looked at,
it was a small study
so I don't know if it generalizes
it will hold up when it's done larger,
but people who have young kids,
you know if you have young kids,
I have three kids
and when they were little
I had colds all the time.
People with young kids are
less likely to die from it.
- And that really tells you something
like, I remember I had
a severe cold actually
just in January
before it was really widely prevalent
and I never had antibody
testing or anything.
So I don't know if it was
COVID, but I doubt it.
No one else in the family was sick.
I caught it from a friend
who was in Las Vegas.
And I wonder whether getting those
really jazzes your T-cell immunity
kind of like getting a BCG vaccination
or something like that.
- There seems to be increasing evidence
that T cell mediated immunity
does matter quite a bit.
- But even talking about that
people are like, "stop
minimizing the catastrophe."
- I don't understand this,
like this is not politics to me.
This is a really important
epidemiologic phenomenon
that we absolutely have
to get our hands around.
We need the best science possible.
I don't understand the politicization
of you're on team apocalypse
or you're on team doom, right, team--
- Team denial.
- [Dr. Jay] Yeah, exactly.
- I liked that team apocalypse
versus team denial go!
That's really what it is.
And we say that we don't understand it,
but we do understand it's
an election year all that,
but as scientists, we don't condone it
is what we're trying to say.
You got sucked into it, right?
Because by definition
now you're on team denial
because you did science
that doesn't support
the press' narrative of X, Y, and Z.
- Yeah, what I was taught
in public health circles,
we actually give people
the right information,
the true information.
We don't unduly stoke panic
just in order to get the result we want,
which is essentially you're gonna comply
with this order or that order.
We don't do that.
We tell people, okay, here are the risks.
We have to trust people to
react to that appropriately.
Not many times, they won't some
but many times they will,
but on net if you wanna maintain trust
in the public health community,
the absolute first thing we have to do
is tell them the absolute
truth about what we know
and we don't know.
- So what you've nailed here again,
is something I talked with
Vinay Prasad on the show about
which is authenticity.
We suck at it in medicine,
we prevaricate, we think
we don't trust the public
to do the right thing.
We are paternalistic to a fault.
So when Monica was on the show yesterday,
she said, you know, I'm an HIV researcher.
I believe in harm reduction.
How dare us preach at people
wear mask you dummy, you stupid person.
And do you wanna kill grandmothers?
And this and this and this,
that's not the way to
communicate public health.
You communicate the uncertainty,
but you communicate what we know
and her whole thing as well,
if mass reduce inoculum,
and it's a low risk intervention,
then maybe you guys should do that.
But it's your decision.
I don't wanna mandate it.
And if we get 80% compliance
according to our data,
maybe that's a tipping point,
but you know, again, it's a hypothesis.
- I'd amend that a little bit.
I agree with that actually,
but the only thing I'd amend
is it's related to the harm
you really, really are seeing.
So if we really are seeing
it's a 3% mortality disease,
yeah then I'm okay with more aggressive.
But if on the other hand
we're really uncertain about that 3%,
which we were.
If we really don't know,
we should tell people,
look, it's looking like 3%
we don't know, let's see,
here's what we're doing
to try to figure it out.
We should just be honest
about what we don't know.
I think to me has been
the most shocking thing
that the public health people and doctors
have dawn this mantle
of absolute knowledge
in a place where I've read
a lot of this literature
there's a lot I don't know
even though I've been reading
the literature scientifically.
So we just don't know.
We should say that.
Why is it bad to say that
when we just don't know.
- You know, and what it does
there's a side effect of that,
that we're seeing now,
which is when doctors and
public health officials
say, "don't wear a mask."
and then yeah in the next
breath, "wear a mask of any kind.
"I don't care
"if it's just the lace panties
over your face wear that"
we look like idiots.
And on top of that,
the public then, which isn't as dumb
as they're portrayed by
the intellectual elite,
goes, "now wait a minute."
- And they should.
And then what happens is,
and you see it in the comments
to my own videos, right?
If I do a video kind of
leaning in one direction,
a billion people comment
the other direction.
If I lean in, in that other direction,
a billion people comment,
the public is trying to find truth.
- Right.
- [Dr. Z] And it's tough.
- I mean, you know, that's okay.
We're having a conversation,
there's stuff I'm learning from you.
I hope there's some stuff
you're learning from me.
And basically that's what science is.
It's a conversation
that leads to more data
that leads to more conversation.
That's what it is.
- So what you just said
is absolutely reasonable and rational
and Buzzfeed attacks your family.
- Yeah, so, I mean, that was tough,
I have to say.
That was probably the hardest parts
of the whole work on this
was just feeling like I've
dragged my family into something.
There's one thing to go after me.
It's, another thing.
Like, but in any case,
let's leave me aside.
So we put this paper out,
we find this number 0.2 to 0.3,
and then a whole series of
studies started coming out
from around the world
to find the same number.
Many of them published,
the peer review literature I
think now has established it.
- So let me ask you a question though.
So what, two to three times a flu
is still catastrophic, man.
Well, how do you respond to that?
- I'd amend that, there's also no vaccine.
- Right no vaccine and we
didn't have treatments.
- Absolutely it is worse than
the flu for those reasons.
- Thank you 'cause I
think that the denial,
I think a lot of people perceive a denial.
This comparison with flu is very charged
and the truth is--
- It's worse than the flu.
And I think for older people,
it is absolutely
we should treat it
like it's much worse than the flu,
because it is worse than the flu.
So for instance, nursing homes, right?
So I just looked at a paper
that said that nursing homes
often share staff workers.
So like one staff worker
works in nursing A
may also works in nursing on B.
We should be using our testing resources
to make sure that when
shared staff workers
move back and forth,
they don't bring the virus
back and forth with them
across these nursing homes.
That seems like a completely
reasonable outcome
of the fact that older people
are much more vulnerable,
especially people with
comorbid conditions.
- And you've been a big advocate
of protecting vulnerable groups.
- That's the whole point of this
is to learn who really should we be using
our relatively limited
resources to protect.
And when we raise alarm,
who should we be doing it for.
There's cost to raising alarm, right?
So like, if I panic you,
you may take actions.
That's the whole point
of the raising the panic and the alarm.
But those actions will
have very little effect
or much less effect on the spread
than the costs that you pay
and the society pays for those acts.
- And the problem with those costs
are they're often in tangibles,
like I have had fans,
who've become fans of my show
since we started the COVID adventure.
And the reason they became fans
is they have generalized anxiety disorder,
or they have some level of anxiety.
They have been jumping out of their skin,
watching the press
catastrophize about this
in generating the fear
that I think was the medical establishment
was complicit with
because they are seeing
it on the front lines
in a very biased way.
Oh my God, my ICU is full
of people who are dying,
including some young people.
And therefore anything we can do
to get the public to behave
is gonna be important, right.
And then what ends up happening
is these poor individuals
who have a tendency to anxiety
are losing their minds.
So they tell me,
I watch your show
because you seem rational
and you have opposing viewpoints,
and you're not just saying
we're all gonna die.
And I think why should I be
the one who's doing that?
- Well, you have a good audience.
- I think that ought to be the general.
- I agree with that.
I don't really understand it,
but it seems like people want,
especially the press seems
to want to create this panic.
So every time there's
a study that comes out,
that a child has died,
which has happened
absolutely for this disease.
You're gonna get this panic
headline from the press.
Now, one of the things I've learned
from the seroprevalence studies,
again from around the world now,
not just mine,
is that there's a very wide
range of clinical presentations
from this disease.
It ranges from, somewhere
between 30 to 40%
of the people that get it
have no symptoms whatsoever.
They can't remember.
They have the antibodies,
but they have no symptoms
that they can remember from it
maybe even a larger part have
relatively mild symptoms.
It's like a cold.
And a small fraction
have this horrible viral
pneumonia that kills them.
We focus all our attention
on the viral pneumonia
and none on the fact that 998 people
are gonna recover from it.
- Yeah, that's a feel good hit
of the summer, right there.
Like that's a positive story
and they're going to develop immunity
and this whole panic
about, well, no, we're never immune.
That's another press thing.
- Yeah.
- [Dr. Z] It's insane
- It's like no other
virus does that, right.
- Exactly well, what do we all,
and the related piece to that,
like you said, one story about a child.
- HIV, I guess
- [Dr. Z] HIV I guess, strep throat.
You can't have a vaccine.
- So actually it's a
legitimate scientific question,
but one we now have an answer to.
You do develop immunity, this virus.
- And the thing is because
we have now millions of cases
and we can look
and there's been like, I
think two documented cases
of actual re-infection.
- [Dr. Jay] Yeah.
- One was like, it was totally mild.
The other was more severe.
And so you could think in a population
there's variants, right.
- But two out of millions right?
So, and as you said, the first case,
that was the reinfection,
it looked like the guy was protected.
- Mild, which is what you would expect,
even with a cold,
like, you get a cold one year,
you may get it again the next year,
but it's gonna be minor.
- Yeah, if you have the same virus,
even if the antibodies fade,
you may have T-cells or
other mechanisms immunity
that make it so that,
it's not that you won't get sick,
but you'll get sick much less
and it won't create severe illness.
- Now, one thing that's gonna come up,
and this comes up a lot again,
in the catastrophization camp,
but what about the long
haulers and the terrible damage
to the lungs and the cardiac damage
and the brain damage
and all the other things.
- You know, those happened with influenza.
- [Dr. Z] Exactly, right.
- So my son, my young son, 13 year old now
a couple years ago, got the flu
and he'd had the flu vaccine
and he still got the flu.
- Which happens.
- Yeah, it happens I mean it was fine.
Like, it was a little worse
than I thought it would
when you normally would get,
and he was getting better
and he woke up one morning
and he couldn't walk.
- [Dr. Z] Oh my gosh.
- I was going through all the panic things
when you go through medical
school, you always have to.
- Like Guillain-Barre.
- That's exactly
- Transverse myelitis.
- And I'm like, Oh God.
So it turned out it was benign myositis.
Thank God and within a
week he was walking again.
Flu has all kinds of strange side effects.
It has neurologic side effects.
It can have cardiac side effects.
We put these in context, right?
These are things that happen.
Absolutely can happen.
but we have a lot of information
about how frequent they are.
Are they likely?
How long lasting they are?
If it was Guillain-Barre
would have been terrible,
but if it's benign myositis it'd last week
and he's okay.
- So that's funny because my
daughter had a viral syndrome
when she was three and couldn't walk
and again benign myositis.
But again, you go through the panic,
but the point being these things happen
with viral infection,
this is a new viral infection
that we don't have a vaccine for.
That is novel to the
degree that it's novel.
Although we seem to have
some innate immunity
from cross-reactivity to Corona Virus,
and yet we are spinning it
as if the world is ending.
And the thing is that would be fine
if we thought it was actually
going to cause less harm
to spin it that way than not,
but it's actually causing a lot of harm
in terms of the response.
So whether it's suicide rate going up,
substance abuse, economic catastrophe,
mortgaging our children's future,
creating intergenerational divides now.
- Yeah, I was hoping we
get to talk about that.
'Cause that's something
I think has been vastly underemphasized
and it's breaking my heart.
So let's talk about suicide.
The CDC released a report, I think in July
that it was a report where they
ask about suicidal ideation.
Like how many suicidal thoughts,
have you have you had any
serious suicidal thoughts.
One in four 18 to 24 year olds,
one in four 18 to 24 year olds in June
had serious thoughts of suicide.
- You know, so my assistant
is in her early twenties
and she only just recently told me
during the early lockdown stuff,
we didn't have her in our house.
And, kind of kept her on a, not a furlough
we were paying her, but she isolated.
Now this is a hyper social
person in the prime of her life
who is now told, don't leave your house
sit there with your dog.
And she told me now that it
was so awful for her, you know?
- Yeah, for a disease for
her 20 early twenties,
probably one in 10,000 death rate.
We're basically imposing
asking young people
who are meant to live in community.
Not me I was a hermit,
but everyone,
- Me too, I really enjoy this.
- But we're not meant to live
alone in our house hold up,
it's going to have consequences.
It's gonna have severe
negative consequences,
psychologically, and we
are already seeing it.
That is just the beginning
of the cost of the lockdown.
Worldwide, they're reports
of hundreds, of millions,
of additional people starving as a result
because you said you're
talking about economics.
So one of the themes I've
heard argued against me
when I make this point
is, well, look, you're
talking about the lockdowns
and there's some economic costs,
but what are they relative
to the lives we save.
But it's not lives on one
side the economy on the other.
The economy is really important
to the lives of the people
who are in the midst of it.
And hundreds of millions
of people around the world
that are on the edge of economic disaster.
And you push them over you,
you destroy the world economy.
It's not just dollars.
It's hundreds of millions
of people starving.
And that's what the UN has said.
Then you go, and it's fine.
- I said this, like in the
first month of this pandemic,
I said, you guys seem to
have this false dichotomy
between economy and lives.
Blood is treasure it's there
it's a transitive property.
When you start having unemployment,
the suicide rate goes up
in the world when you
shut the economy down,
people starved to death.
And this idea,
and I'm gonna rant for one second
and you may or may not agree with me.
I feel like my own tribe of people,
the healthcare professionals,
have held the rest of our country hostage
with their catastrophizing around this,
which was done with good intent.
These are good smart people.
And they're right.
We've had deaths and terrible outcomes,
but they fail to see the bigger picture.
And Monica Gandhi on
the show yesterday said,
as doctors it's our
responsibility to see this.
- Our job is to show people that picture,
I'd say even more than just,
I mean, I call us the
Zoomocracy and I mean it.
So like, I'm fine
I can be on Zoom and
I'm not going to lose my
well, maybe who knows the
Sanford could keep me.
- We gotta talk about that.
- But I think I'm fine, right?
So like, why should I care about,
well, my job is to tell people
what's happening in the
rest of the world, I think.
There's this program called Gavi,
which is a program for vaccinations
International Program for Vaccinations.
They've halted their operations
because of the lockdown.
- So polio comes back,
measles comes back.
measles never gone, measles is still here.
- Yeah we're gonna see research
we may even see resurgents
in polio in the United States
because people stopped taking their kids
for the Tdap vaccine.
- Yeah absolutely cancer screening,
their mental--
- So we've had good news from
cancer for the past few years.
We've actually had decreases
in cancer related mortality
for the first time in my memory anyways,
for three or four years in a row
that will reverse,
we're gonna start seeing
later stage breast cancers,
later stage prostate cancers,
people stopped getting screening.
People actually even
stopped getting treatment
for cancer, active cancer.
During the epidemic.
- Yeah I've seen that.
HIV, patients are losing
their viral suppression.
Monica was talking about that
because they're not coming in.
- Tuberculosis millions of
extra tuberculosis cases
'cause you have tuberculosis,
you have to treat over
a long period of time
with regular antibiotics.
People come in around the world
because they're--
- Directly observed therapy,
all this other stuff.
- Exactly and that stopped
were gonna see a resurgence
of tuberculosis deaths.
- Well, so let me ask a question
because this is very gloomy stuff.
Like, honestly, when you said earlier,
you were heartbroken.
This is what keeps me up at night
because you know here
we have this platform
we can get to see,
like you said, we're
part of the Zoomocracy.
Like we can do this,
we can get this information out,
but it doesn't sink in.
And what it does is, I worry
that it even contributes more
to this polarization
because there are camps
that get so emotional
about the damage we've
done from our response
and camps that gets so emotional
from The United States' perceived failure
relative to other countries
in terms of mortality per million.
- I'm heartbroken at both.
I mean, I think we in public
health need to balance
COVID is not the only
threat to public health.
We need to understand
that there's all kinds of
public health problems.
- So what do you think you would say
The United States should do?
And then I wanna talk
about Sweden and Europe and Asia too,
but what do you think the
United States should do?
So here's the problem,
all this disaster from our response
and then the danger of the virus,
which is worse for the elders
and people with comorbidities.
And it's blessed than
we thought initially.
And we have a little better treatment now.
So what do you think?
- If I had to characterize
the American response.
It's exactly backwards.
- [Dr. Z] Yes.
- We have quarantined the healthy
and we've exposed the
vulnerable to the disease.
- That's it and Monica said yesterday.
- [Dr. Jay] Flip that around.
- Monica said yesterday, we
were exactly backwards as well.
We've favored the rich
people who can survive this,
the Zoomocracy like you and I,
and we've punished the poor.
So we've actually told them,
stay inside, lose your jobs,
get $1,200 a month.
- Yeah, or you go out and expose yourself,
deliver the groceries to
- Essential worker.
- Yeah, I don't understand it.
I could understand three in a 100 deaths.
- Different story
- You imagine it,
but even there you'd wanna focus response
and figure out who really is
- In that 3%.
- Right, exactly and there may be people
who are less vulnerable.
You tailor your strategy around
the numbers you're seeing,
but we haven't done that yet.
We've gone the opposite
route since in many ways,
I think New York is an absolute disaster,
New York, I mean,
the highest death rates in the world
happened in the Northeast
early map of the United States.
- Yeah and multiple
reasons for that probably
that will become clear
also more in retrospect
and our retrospectoscope
is is gonna be highly, highly indicting.
I think of a lot of behavior
that we had early on.
- Yeah, can we return to,
you were asking me earlier
about like the scientific
discussion around this.
- Yeah, I would love to,
- So I've been really concerned
about censorship in science
around this epidemic.
- As have I.
- Yeah and so like you mentioned,
John Ioannidis is one of the foremost
physicians in the world,
researchers in the world studying.
I had the honor to be
able to work with him.
He did an interview
early on in the epidemic
that was suppressed by YouTube.
- How do you suppress John Ioannidis?
- I don't know, I don't understand it.
My view of science is
that it's a conversation.
We have to have the ability
to express views that are not popular
or else we can't have a science.
We can't have science.
- I mean.
- So the idea
is that somehow if somebody
is expressing a view
that is contrary to
somebody's interpretation
of some public health organization,
World Health Organization or whatever,
it's ipso facto dangerous
to say those views,
that is a form of population control.
That's what it is, right.
- It really is, yeah.
- It's fine if you know,
with 100% scientific certainty,
that some fact--
- Is wrong.
- Yes.
- Yeah, like vaccines cause autism, right?
- So what's the your response.
You say, look, the vaccines
don't cause autism, right?
That's the right response.
- [Dr. Z] That's right.
- And here's the evidence.
- If you have a situation of a new virus
where the science is emerging rapidly
and we're learning new things,
I've changed my mind about 15 things
about this virus
as I've read new papers
- [Dr. Z] Me too.
- over the course,
how could you not?
- Yeah but you know what, read
the comments in my videos.
You flip-flopped on this five times.
- Got me with this new
evidence coming up right.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- So in that context,
scientific censorship is criminal.
- Yeah. I agree.
- And so I think,
and we've seen this over and over again,
there's a set of papers
by this scientist, Gabriella Gomez
on the Herd Immunity threshold.
- [Dr. Z] I love her work, yeah.
- And what I've seen her write
is that she sent her paper
to scientific journals
the editors won't even
send it out for review
because they're saying
that it's too dangerous
her findings suggest a lower
Herd Immunity threshold.
Now I don't know if it's
right or wrong, I don't--
- Does it matter?
- Well, let's just have a
scientific conversation about it.
Why is that so dangerous to talk about
that you wouldn't even
send it out for review?
- I mean, the last time
we did stuff like this,
it was the inquisition in Galileo.
- I felt a little like that Stanford.
I think the,
- Tell me about it
- well, we'll talk about
that in just a bit.
But I think the knee jerk reaction
to censor people that you disagree with
inside the scientific community
has been absolutely terrible.
One of my Stanford colleagues
actually wrote a New York Times article
arguing for essentially a censorship board
for our articles in Nova Science.
- Hey, look, I kind of am an expert
in misinformation management.
I have always, look, remember
those Bakersfield Docs,
they were proposing some similar ideas
to what you were saying,
but their, their data was
a little and you know,
they were clearly a little.
- I've talked to them,
look, there's stuff I agree with it,
but there's stuff, I don't
necessarily agree with them,
but why should they not be
part of the conversation?
- Exactly, so when that video came out,
a million people sent it to
me, what do you think of this?
And I said, well, let me
do a show on what I think.
I agree with them that
lockdowns are harmful.
I agree with them we're
overreacting creating fear.
I disagree with their use of the data
on this and this and this.
And I disagree that
YouTube pulled their clip.
- Yeah it's ridiculous.
- Why would you do that?
All you're gonna do is
also solidify this idea
that there's a conspiracy.
- I think the idea that media
organizations or Stanford
has some obligation to
censor opposing views
is absolutely anathema to science.
- And you know, my wife is
on a Listserv at Stanford.
So a bunch of people
that I know at Stanford
got on a Listserv on the
Stanford listserv email
and said, "we hear by
disavow Scott Atlas."
- Oh, that's disgusting.
- Yeah so can you tell
me a little about that?
- Sure, so again one of my
colleagues sign that letter too.
You know people I respect.
- [Dr. Z] People I respect
to know are on that.
- People I love are on that list.
I mean like friends,
I mean, I disagree with them
about some of the things.
- Right, but we can
love people and disagree
without shutting them up.
- So think Dr. Atlas Scott
is the Special Advisor to
the President on COVID.
He has certain views
about the nature of the epidemic.
They're actually closer to
my views than by colleagues.
So among those views
are things like the disease
is less dangerous for kids,
less dangerous than the flu for kids.
That seems like there's
solid scientific evidence.
And yet the letter it seems
to like paint this picture
about the danger to kids.
I think my colleagues
are just wrong on this.
The way they disagree with Scott on this,
- I agree when I read the letter,
I'm like, these guys are just wrong.
They haven't read what Scott is saying.
Now, look, I don't agree
with Scott on everything.
- So now I think they've
also mischaracterized
what Scott has said.
So for instance, Scott has repeatedly said
that he's not in favor of
a Herd Immunity strategy.
Actually, we should talk a
little bit about Herd Immunity
- Herd Immunity Strategy.
- What does that actually mean?
Herd Immunity means that,
so when we think about Herd Immunity,
if we think about it as a single number,
but it's again, just
like infection fatality
is not a single number.
What Herd Immunity means
is that when a new
person gets the disease,
how many people are
they gonna spread it to?
If it's less than one, then
you reached Herd Immunity.
- It's gonna be squashed.
- Exactly, if there's more than one,
then you get more sort of
this exponential growth right.
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- That happens with every disease
where immunity actually happens,
that's just normal.
The number is a function of
how people interact in society.
So if I interact with a lot of people
and I get it, I will spread it.
If I'm sort of more
fearful about the disease
and I spreading it,
then then social distancing happens
then Herd Immunity, could get
lower to meet the thresholds.
'Cause one person getting it,
doesn't spread to a lot of people.
So it's a function of
the behavior of people,
as well as again, the virus itself,
it's not a single number
where you say, okay,
here's, we've reached it.
And ironically, you can reach it
cases are declining
and people stop taking those precautions.
and it goes back up again.
We can go in and out of Herd Immunity.
- Right, autoregulation homeostasis
of the population's behavior.
- Yeah, exactly so that's actually,
it's more complicated than that.
Personally Scott has told me,
I've never told the president
that he's in favor of
Herd Immunity strategy.
He is not.
He specifically said that the
letter my colleagues wrote
accused him of that, just falsely.
It's just, if you set up the straw, man,
I mean, I just, I don't understand it.
It's like they weren't listening
and partly it's the press's fault.
Like the press has
mischaracterized him as well.
- For sure, this is what I think happened.
And honestly, and you can correct me.
They read the press,
they read some CNN, MSNBC
Scott, Atlas doesn't knows
nothing about science.
And he's got president's ear.
- He was the Chair of Neuroradiology
at Stanford for years.
I mean, I just don't,
- My wife worked with him right.
And the thing is, if you hear him talk
again, he's reiterating some
of the concerns that we have.
He's never said,
let it rip through the
population and develop.
- That's that's the
exact opposite strategy.
I know he's been telling the president.
- Right, right and the thing
is, you've talked to him,
have these colleagues talk to him, no.
And this is what happens.
You have in-group.
This is his tribe of people.
Now excommunicating him
and which hunting him
because that's what's
happening on social media.
That's what's happening
in the halls of academia.
Is this how you met him?
Okay just play with this for a second.
What if your right and Neeraj is right.
And in retrospect we realize
you guys were actually
banging the right drum
and these people who
censored, you were wrong.
Okay, that is gonna be a
criminal act that they did.
That costs lives.
- Yeah, I think there was an
attempt to cancel me right.
- [Dr. Z] Oh, for sure.
- I don't actually care I get canceled.
What I really want is the
data to drive the policy.
That's what I really want.
And I think Scott would
say the same thing.
I mean, it's just not personal for him.
It's like, let's let the
data drive the policy.
Cause the cost on lies are high
on both sides of this decision.
There's no riskless option here.
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- So whether you lock
down or don't lock down
is not a, okay, let's
just stay safe on one side
so my colleagues started the letter
with the principle of do no harm.
How do you do no harm in this situation?
- There's plenty of ways to
do harm sensor a colleague.
- [Dr. Jay] For instance.
- On insufficient information.
Now, I imagine,
okay, so let's dig into
that a little more,
and you can refuse to
answer this if you like.
Your own paper was attacked internally
in a almost politicized way.
It wasn't so much about the science.
And I was reading these things
about the internecine
drama at Stanford.
And I'm like, I know these
people, what are they doing?
- It was absolutely shocking to me.
I feel like my academic
freedom was attacked
and I've been at the university
for 30 plus years actually
the motto of the university
is "Let The Winds of Freedom Blow."
I don't think that they acted,
the leaders of the university
have acted in that way
toward my study.
And it's been absolutely shocking to me.
- Are you tenured?
- I am.
- Okay, so you can say this kind of thing.
- Well, I don't care if I lose my job.
- You know what I'll hire you.
We could be like ,
you know, we could have one
of these like Sunday mornings
- It's been really
enjoyable talking to you
- Bhattacharya that would be really fun.
So to this thing, I was shocked when I saw
how this thing was played out.
And I knew that what
the press was reporting,
wasn't the full story.
It was still concerning.
I was like, well, is
there a lot of bias here
is this thing, you know?
And so I was waiting to
talk to you about this.
And you know, at some point
I'll have one of the colleagues
that's attacking you guys on the show
and see what they think.
'Cause it'd be interesting, right.
- [Dr. Jay] Yeah.
- But I would love to see that play out
in a way that isn't just politicized.
Cause it's this.
- Yeah I got to do a
debate with Stan Vermund.
- Oh yeah I know Stan.
I know of Stan.
- Yeah, so it was really interesting.
Like he's a Yale,
the Head of the Public
Health Department at Yale.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- Really sweet guy.
- Talked really slow
I was listening to
debate going , oh my God
I got to put it up to three X.
Except when you talk, then
I had to slow it down.
- [Dr. Jay] I'm sorry.
- No, no I love fast talkers.
- I bet but I think is that he's open.
He wants to talk.
He wants to have a conversation.
I wish we had that spirit of Stanford.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- I think in some ways we have lost that
and it's been dispiriting for me.
- Yeah. I agree.
Well, you know, the two folks
that I interviewed from
UCSF, Monica and Vinay
are deeply embodied that spirit
of open discourse.
They may politically disagree.
It doesn't matter.
They only wanna have the conversation
in a polite and civil way.
- Yeah, I mean, I that's the thing,
Internally I don't think,
I don't know what joining
these politics are.
I have literally no idea.
I don't and I'm pretty sure
if I were to talk with Eran
that we would disagree about politics.
It doesn't matter, we're doing science,
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- Like we move to what the data tell us.
- Eran Bendavid who was also a resident
when I was an attending there.
I'm gonna try to have
him on the show later.
- Yeah he was the lead author
on the Santa Clara Study.
- Yeah so I can dig in a
little more with him, yeah.
It's great to be next to all
these smart people, you know.
But so it's been just a mess.
It's been hard I imagine.
Forget, it's been hard on you
clearly, you and your family,
but secondary thing that has been hard
on our scientific advancement
and understanding this virus
because when you suppress these ideas,
what happens?
They pop up on Twitter
in a weaponized form.
So now you have frank anti maskers
that are taking masks and
ripping out the lining
so that they can do the hygiene theater
without the actual filter.
You know, I mean this crazy stuff,
none of that would have happened
if we'd just been open and honest.
- Yeah, I think it's the same thing
with the anti-vaxxers right.
So like
- [Dr. Z] Same thing.
- Actually, the funny thing is like
we should talk about the vaccines.
- Let's just say that, yeah.
- But I think if a vaccine does
come out and it's effective.
The fact that the scientific
community is acting this way
will create doubt around the vaccine.
- Who's gonna get it?
40% of Americans don't want to get it now.
- Yeah and because the
scientific community
is very, very clearly seems
politicized around this.
- 1000% and remember in
the early days of fear,
when we were in the Imperial
college sphere of influence,
and we thought 3 million
Americans were gonna die,
there was not an anti-vaxx
voice to be heard.
They were terrified.
They wouldn't open their mouth.
They saw, oh, 'cause
when push comes to shove,
if there's a vaccine,
they're gonna be first in line to get it
when you're afraid for your life.
But then as this thing spun out now,
they've actually been empowered in a way
that we haven't remembered in recent.
- It's because the scientific
community is screwed up.
- [Dr. Z] They've made
idiots of themselves.
- Yeah.
- Does it make you want to
hit stuff and throw stuff.
'cause I get emotional about it.
- I'm not built that way.
- I forget sometimes
that I'm talking to scientific introverts
who have like spock like controls,
whereas I'm the opposite.
I'm just like throw the table
over and kill everybody.
- Well, when, when they
were talking to my wife,
you know that means--
- [Dr. Z] That's too much.
- But other than that I
still just want to know
what the right thing to do is.
- Right, there've been things
where I've gone back and forth
because I'm not convinced
one way or the other.
And I will literally sit up at night
going I put out a video today saying this
and is it really a 100% right?
No, it can't be a 100% right
'cause we don't know yet.
So am I doing more harm
than good saying it,
what's the harm reduction.
- You have to say what
you currently believe.
And then when you find new
evidence you change your mind
you say it.
- That's the thing.
So that's what it is.
But, but it's hard.
For me it's emotionally difficult
because I tend to
involute this emotionally.
Whereas again, that's
why I'm not a researcher.
So a researcher I could have
a little more equanimity.
- I mean,
- [Dr. Z] It's meditation,
- it's hard to admit
that you're wrong right.
That's just, but look, you
can't do science without that,
'cause new data come out
and you change your mind.
- So let me ask you a
question, speaking of data.
So, and I've been meaning
to ask this of you.
So you read an Atlantic
article, all right.
And it says, here's all
the cognitive distortions
that we've shown in this thing.
And it was the actually
the opposite version
of what I've been saying,
which is here are the
cognitive distortions
that we've are showing
that cause us to catastrophize
and misunderstand
the science on this.
They were saying, well,
here's all the reasons
that America screwed it up
and not taking it seriously and so on.
And we have this terrible mortality rate
and the high case rate and all that.
And they would say things in
there just throw away things
like, and then they're Sweden's policy,
which is folly and they put a link
and they wished they hadn't done.
How do you respond to that?
- I mean, U.S has higher death
rate than Sweden right now.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- More cases per million in
the United States than Sweden.
To characterize Sweden as a failure
seems like, I mean they've made mistakes.
It's in the early days, I think
- Not protecting the elderly.
- Yeah, they wait until early April
to essentially protect the
nursing homes in a serious way.
And I think that led to
some of their higher deaths,
but that's the same way
U.S made the same mistake.
- We did the same thing.
45% of deaths were nursing home patients
0.6% of the population.
So Sweden actually took a
very different approach.
- I think it's more consistent
with what a democracy does
in the context of these
kinds of things, right?
So the idea of the
lockdown we were copying,
what Japan, oh, sorry not
Japan, what China did.
- Right.
- I like this idea
but the idea that we could
do this militarized lockdown,
I don't think is consistent
with a constitutional democracy.
- [Dr. Z] I agree.
- And you're seeing this play out
in places like Australia or Victoria,
where they have essentially
a very draconian lockdown.
You can only go out for an hour.
If you're gonna go to a
park, you have to walk alone.
You know, I don't think that's consistent.
I mean, people will play
with that for a while
if it's a 3% mortality rate.
- [Dr. Z] Sure.
- But they won't put up with it forever.
And that's a constraint on
public health in a democracy.
You have to take that into account.
You can't pretend
like, oh, it's really unfortunate
that people won't put
up with this forever.
- I said that in February.
I said, what we're seeing in Wuhan
is absolutely never going to
be feasible in this democracy.
It's just not.
And you could just say,
well, then people will die
because of that.
Then that's the cost of living
in a constitutional democracy
that you will not have
that kind of control.
And one thing I would say to that
is life is to be lived
we don't live in fear of
death or dismemberment
every single second we're awake.
And that's an ethos that I
think is worth supporting.
And again, that's a
personal thing I mandatory.
- Yeah, but I think
that's completely right.
I think one of the unfortunate
outcomes of this pandemic
has been to train people,
to think of other human beings
as just bags of germs to be avoided.
- You're right.
- It's going to take a long time
to repair the damage from that
- It's a social dissolution.
And then what happens now
we have, you know, unrest
on a massive level.
I'm not saying they're
directly correlated,
but I'm saying they're
directly correlated.
- It wouldn't surprise me.
I think that people are
psychologically frayed.
- Yeah, I am.
Monica, when she came yesterday,
like I said, you don't know me.
The reason she came
was she wanted to talk to
another human being face to face
about things she cares about.
And she has been able to do that.
Zoom is, listen, Zoom is great
from a technological level,
what a wonderful tool, right.
I hate it, it makes me wanna die.
And the reason is I'm an extrovert
and being in the room with someone,
like you and I right now
could not have the same conversation.
I'm reading your body
language in real time.
It's a 2000 frame per second refresh rate.
You know we're able to
talk over each other.
It's a beautiful thing that humans do.
- Yeah and we're built
for this kind of community
we're built for this
kind of communication.
And we're not built to be alone,
which is essentially what
this epidemic has done.
And the public health community
said, look, that's what you need to do.
- That's what you need to
They're telling you be inhuman.
- [Dr. Jay] Yeah.
- And also now we changed our mind
being human in this way,
instead of out there.
Let me ask you something.
So you look at the Asian countries
cause you can look
okay, okay U.S, Sweden,
U.K, deaths, deaths.
- [Dr. Jay] Yeah.
- Then you get to European Union deaths
and then you get to New
Zealand, Singapore, Hong Kong,
whoa, actual viral suppression.
- I think there's a few
lessons to be learned for this.
So New Zealand let's
come back to New Zealand.
New Zealand is really, it's
super interesting on this front.
I think that some of the Asian nations
that suppressed the virus,
they caught it very early on
when contact tracing
the kinds of things that we say
are like the mantra of like
test trace and quarantine
actually can be effective.
- Early
- Early, but by early April,
50,000 cases in Santa Clara alone,
- [Dr. Z] It's out of the bag.
- I don't understand why people thought
that that was go work.
- And how do you contact
trace asymptomatic cases.
You'd have to test everyone
hope there aren't a bunch
of false positives yeah.
- Yeah so I think that
was a thinking mistake
that the virus wasn't so widespread,
we could use this strategy
that seems like it was
working in Asian countries,
but even in the Asian countries,
I think there's some evidence that the,
we talk about cross-reactive immunity.
Like there were other
Corona Virus like infections
that they've had,
they may have had
some more extensive
cross-reactive immunity
more prevalent cross-reactive immunity
than European countries and the U.S had.
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- So I mean, I don't know.
- SARS-ish, yeah.
- Who knows?
- Who knows right?
- So I think we don't know fully
why it didn't hit the
Asian countries as hard
I think it's important to think about
New Zealand is a really
super interesting example.
They famously suppressed the disease
at zero cases for 120 days.
And then out of nowhere, the
cases start rising again.
Okay, well, what did they do?
They locked down again.
The problem is like that
lockdown is now repeated forever.
They have to keep repeating the lockdown
over and over again.
- Or they'll just go through
what we went through.
- And they're an Island nation
that depends on tourism.
I mean fully, I think just like 10% of,
very large fraction of GDP.
Don't quote me on the number,
but that large fraction of GDP
is gone basically permanently
because who wants to
sit on 14 day quarantine
to visit someplace.
And people leaving the
Island are also gone already,
so there's just the traffic
in and out of the islands out
So what you have is a continuous,
and they've had like a
seven to 10% decrease
in their GDP rate just this year.
You don't keep that.
If you wanna isolate yourself
from the rest of the world,
you can do it, but it's
gonna take you enormous.
It's gonna be enormous cost.
And that is not an option
available in the United States.
- Yeah absolutely, so the
New Zealand experience
is interesting because they
are relying on something
that may or may not happen,
which is a safe and effective
vaccine as their savior,
because what else could
they be waiting for?
It's always gonna exist in the community
at some level otherwise
we have to learn to live with it.
And their way of living with it
is shutting down their
entire Island forever.
But they're probably waiting
for this finish line, right.
- [Dr.  Jay] They're
waiting for the vaccine.
- Now what's the risk of that?
- Well, so the vaccine is,
I have to say that more progress
and rapid progress has
been made on the vaccine
than I anticipated.
If you'd asked me in April,
that we'd be be here with Phase 3 trials,
actually ongoing for
several vaccine candidates.
I would have said there's no chance.
I mean, there aren't any
human Corona Virus vaccines.
- Yeah, often said that Paul
Offit had the same thing
on my show vaccine expert.
So at that time.
- Okay, but now here's the situation
we have these vaccine camps
that many and look promising
in the Phase 2 trials.
The Phase 3 trials
need to be on large populations of people.
Why?
Partly because the cases
and deaths are declining,
ironically, that makes it more difficult
to show that the vaccine is efficacious
because you just,
let's say you had the COVID vaccine
before Corona Virus came along at all.
Well, you'd never find it efficacious
in preventing death
because there was no risk of Corona Virus.
- Exactly, right, we're
making it harder now.
- So the decline of the cases
and the decline in deaths
makes it harder to show the vaccine works.
- Yeah, yeah and that's
gonna make it more difficult
to show efficacy.
Safety we could still study.
- Yeah safety we could study.
And there've been some
good news and bad news.
Like many of the vaccine
candidates have been safe.
In Phase 1 and phase,
but they're reports now
there's a Transverse Myelitis.
- Transverse Myelitis case
in the UK, Astra Zeneca,
now that's a different
a viral model, right.
Adenovirus, yeah.
So it's a different than the mRNA vehicle.
- The mRNA vehicle hasn't really been used
in human vaccines before
- Ever, exactly, so it's totally novel.
- So I mean, it could work.
It could still work, I think I'm waiting.
I mean, if the data show
that it's safe and effective,
I'll be first.
- I'll first in line I
have to look at that data.
People have asked me,
what will you and your
kids get this thing?
Well, I'll tell you what,
as soon as I am convinced
that the data looks good,
I'll go do it because I
would like to get on a plane
and go do things without thinking,
well, I'm 47 so my risk profile is X.
I have genetic clotting disorders
and so endothelial dysfunction.
So my risk is somewhere in the X.
That's how I calculate my own risk.
So I take reasonable precautions,
but I'm not crazy
because I desperately
seek human connection
and I'm willing to die rather than.
- It's probably two to
three in 1,000 for me.
Yeah I would rather live my life
with that two to three in 1,000 risks.
If I happen to get it than not.
- But you're going to kill grandma
by asymptomatically spreading it to her.
- When I visited my 80 year
old mom, I wore a mask.
- There you go.
And that's what I would
do with my parents.
So let me think here.
What you just said is be rational.
Take risk personally and
decide based on open data.
Don't sensor people, let's have
actual scientific discourse
instead of name calling
and politicization.
And let's look at this
thing with clear, open eyes
and listen to all viewpoints.
Is that about right?
- I mean, I've tried to be controversial.
- Well, you've done a good
job by proxy in person
and I haven't heard
anything that you've said
that makes me go,
oh my gosh, that's so controversial.
It's called being rational.
Now the thing is,
I'll get criticism even
on during this interview
that, oh, did you really
pound them on this
and pound him on that?
That's not my job.
My job is to say,
here is a guy who has a
certain experience set
that's very valuable.
Let him talk about what he thinks
and you guys can then debate
it in the comments openly.
That's called scientific discourse.
It's actually just discourse.
And sometimes I wonder,
because anything I post,
you know, if I look at
Facebook, for example,
which is our biggest platform,
2 million people follow us there.
If I put something there and
you start reading the comments,
sometimes you wanna die a little
because it's like the movie
"Idiocracy" actually came true
and you just go, oh,
and it's on all sides.
It's all sides.
- I get referee reports
all the time for my papers.
So I'm used to that.
- You're used to it right.
You're used to it.
So, we talked about Sweden a bit.
We talked about New Zealand
and we talked about Asian countries
and why they were different than us.
We talked about the U.S.
We talked about what we might
wanna do moving forward.
So do you think cases are
just gonna continue to decline
and deaths are going to
continue to decline here.
- I mean, there's two
points of view, right?
So one is that there's
gonna be a second wave.
That seems to be the Fowchee
point of view right now.
I don't see much evidence of that.
Like we haven't started, in
the United States for instance,
we talk about if we had a second wave,
in New York and then the second wave,
we hadn't had a second wave,
we had is a regional epidemic.
Each place has had a first wave.
That's what it looks like everywhere.
Now, it's possible
I mean, we don't know
the thing has only been
around a few months
that there could be one,
but it's looking
increasingly unlikely to me,
but we will see.
- I'm with you.
Based on current information,
I can be proven wrong
and I've said this to my supporters,
who there are people who
subscribe to the show
and we do private live shows
there's like 7,000 number out of them.
And I'll tell them things
that I'm not comfortable, fully
vetted out for the public.
So I go this is my feeling
right now based on data
is that there is not a second wave
in this classic sense,
there may be a second wave casedemic
where we start testing a lot.
And we see a lot of asymptomatic,
positive PCR fragments.
The second thing is what
people don't seem to understand
is that the first wave, like you said,
was a geographic thing
where in a cooler climates
like the Northeast,
you saw massive rise and then a fall.
In more Southern temperate climates
is what you see what
kind of with influenza,
which is a slower delayed
rise and a low, long hump.
And they're calling that second wave.
That's still all part of
the infectious pattern.
And I think in the winter,
it'll be interesting to see also schools.
Tell me your thoughts on school.
- I think it's criminal
not to open schools.
- [Dr. Z] I agree with you.
- Yeah, we talk about safety.
It is more unsafe to not
let kids go back to school
than to open up for schools.
- Absolutely.
- We are harming kids
in a way that is irreparable and immoral.
- You're gonna get a
horse's head in your bed
from the teacher's union on that one.
- I think a lot of teachers want to be
that's their vocation is to teach
and they wanna teach in person.
How do you teach a first
grader to read over Zoom?
- [Dr. Z] No, it's a crime.
- Yeah.
- And the thing is they're
doing the best they can.
It's very, very hard,
but this is one of the things
that just gets me so upset
because it's a regressive tax on the poor.
So you're saying basically
that a person who depends
on school for their meals,
for their social interaction
for behavior control
mom is a single mom and can't
it's and how is she gonna work
we can hire nannies and
assistants they can't.
- I saw a picture, I think it
was in San Jose, Mercury News
of two kids, Hispanic kids,
sitting outside of a 7-Eleven
with their little Google Chromebooks.
- I saw that
Using the 7-Eleven, the taco bell wifi.
- To wifi 'cause they
don't have wifi at home.
- [Dr. Z] That is disgusting.
- It's terrible.
- It's heartbreaking.
- And you know schools
are not just simply places for teaching,
although that is incredibly important.
- You are Indian I knew it.
It's for teaching only nothing else.
- But there are also places
where kids get their nutrition.
Somewhere I think on the
order of a third of kids
in the country have
subsidized school meals
of some sort or another,
like a lot of their calories
get come from there.
It's places where they learn to socialize.
The long run consequences
of shutting that down
are absolutely enormous.
Even the short run,
I suspect we'll start to see suicides
jump up among adolescents
School is good for their
mental health as well.
- I have a close friend who's a physician
whose daughter was 12, 13.
And during the lockdown started to exhibit
just the worst anxiety.
Like he would describe this to me.
And it was heartbreaking.
This kid was beside herself
and to the point where it was medications
and psychotherapy and all that,
and he affluent guy, so
he can afford all this.
And then school started
some little bit in person,
some little bit by Zoom
and the anxiety started to evaporate
and we forget that we're
the social animals.
And especially kids.
I used to look forward
as much as I love summer,
you look forward to school starting.
'Cause I'm gonna see Joey and Chad
and we're going to hang out
and cause some crime, man.
I mean, that was what it was like.
- Yeah. I agree.
I mean, I think for kids,
especially that playtime
is incredibly psychologically important.
To deny them that seems...
Okay it's one thing
if they're really we're facing high risk.
- So tell me about that
because the teachers will push back
and say, but there's
teachers with chronic disease
who are elderly, who.
- I think we should that into account.
I think like different school districts
should creatively manage that.
So if you're a 62 year old teacher
and you have diabetes,
your school district to make
some accommodation for you.
So you don't have teaching.
- [Dr. Z] Agree.
- Absolutely.
- Do you think we should
be paying teachers
more too in general.
- Yeah.
- [Dr. Z] As an economist.
- I think there's some debate in economics
about how much extra pay
correlates to outcomes.
But as a whole teacher,
I mean, I honor my teachers,
I think they did incredible things for me.
- [Dr. Z] Me too.
- And also for the kids.
So I'm not against that.
I'm fine with that,
But I think we should use the resources,
different school districts
use the resources they have
to creatively manage
so that kids can actually come in person.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- In some places, maybe
you can't social distance,
you need more masks
in places where you can social distance,
you can figure it out.
I mean, you have to
creatively manage that.
Young teachers who face very
little risk, let them come in.
The older teachers who are at risk,
they can maybe they can
help the younger teachers
by helping them grade, create
curriculum, teach online.
I mean, I think there's some mix,
but the absolute must
is you have to have the kids in person.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah, yeah.
- With each other or else you
can't actually have school.
- Now, you know what I
think is happening too.
And it's related to this
is this safety creep.
So in the early days of this thing,
when they talked right here in the Bay
about shutting down schools,
we were thinking it'll
be two, three weeks.
And then they said,
it's gonna be till the end of the year,
the school year
There was absolute horror and panic
on the part of parents and kids
like what, you're doing what.
Now, when school's supposed
to reopen it doesn't
and people have just accepted it as well.
All right we're keeping people safe now.
It's the norm.
Our kids are slowly dying a little
we're destroying poor families.
We're creating a cycle of poverty,
violence, substance abuse,
but you know what?
Safety safety first.
- It's not safe.
- [Dr. Z] It's not safe
it's the opposite of safe.
- Yeah and if you think
about what the scientific
evidence is saying,
the teachers and staff pose
more of a risk to each other
than the kids pose to them.
There's a study done by
this group in Iceland.
It was published in New England Journal.
It's absolutely fascinating.
So what they did is they
took 12% of random sample
of the Icelandic population.
And they did PCR testing on
every single one of them.
And they identified the
virus from every single one
that was positive.
And they sequenced the
genome of every virus.
Why is that important?
Because the virus has
these mutations there,
give it like a fingerprint.
And they did this detailed
contact tracing study where they,
and because they did the genetic analysis,
like let's say, I have
virus A with mutation
and you have virus A and B.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- With mutation A and B.
Well, it's possible
that I passed it to you
because you added on mutation B,
but it's unlikely you pass it to me.
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- And if I have just a mutation A
and you have just mutation B,
then we didn't pass it to each other.
- Right separate sources yeah.
- Okay, what they found was that
there was not one single case
of a child passing into an adult.
- Not one case.
- Many, many cases of parents
passing it to their kids.
- [Dr. Z] Yeah.
- But not one the other way.
- So why are we ignoring this data?
- [Dr. Jay] I don't know.
- And so here's the counter
that the mainstream media will say,
well, look at what's
happening at Notre-Dame
or wherever there's thousands
of cases and, oh, my God.
- Not one hospitalization, by the way.
- [Dr. Z] Not a single one.
- Yeah and I mean, talking
about college kids right.
So there's not one hospitalization.
- Now, but what about these
it's just these horrible vectors
of disease for the elderly.
- I mean, asymptomatic spread happens.
That's what the evidence says,
but it's much less common
than symptomatic spread.
So the diseases spread
by mostly by droplets,
you can have these aerosolization events
it seems like,
but they're relatively rare
compared to the droplet spread,
- [Dr. Z] Right.
- Asymptomatic spread happens,
but it's much more rare.
Just to give you some sense,
Sweden kept its schools open
15 and under including daycare
all the way through the epidemic.
Even when cases were rising,
even deaths were rising.
And they did this detailed
study compared to Finland.
Opening and closing the
schools does not have
any appreciable effect on
the spread of the epidemic.
- The what the hell are we doing?
- I don't know, I don't know.
I think the evidence on this is so strong.
And you read it and you just weep
because you're saying, okay, we're making
a scientifically uninformed decision.
- You know what it is.
It is also coming to this thing
of what I call empathy versus compassion.
So empathy is feeling another
person's pain as your own
and acting from that feeling.
They ask us to do this
in medicine all the time, more empathy.
But what they don't realize
is empathy is a poison
when it comes to things like this,
because here's what happens,
I read an in some mainstream media piece
about a 28 year old teacher
who died of COVID after school was open
and you go, oh, my God,
the young teacher died
we should never have opened the school.
I feel for her and her
family and she's young
and we should just stop everything.
Whereas when you look at the case,
okay, what were the comorbidities?
They were there.
What's going on?
And that's one person.
Did she get it from school?
We don't know, could have
gotten it somewhere else,
but we're going to now fail to do
what we ought to have done,
which is compassion, which
is cognitive empathy.
Understand the suffering.
Look at the bigger picture.
What's the most wise thing
we can do for the most people
to relieve the suffering
and detach a little bit.
Well, if you do that, you
go, actually that's true.
But we could have provided
masks to the teachers
and given schools an opening
so that these children who are
dying of diseases of despair
or are going to, get a chance.
But we don't do that.
- I mean, you're arguing for it.
I mean, that's a really
nice way to put it.
You're arguing for empathy for everybody.
Not just for like the select few.
- And the trick about empathy
is it doesn't work on everybody.
So Paul Bloom has written
about this, psychologist.
It is a narrow spotlight,
not just on individual, but on tribe.
So empathy evolved for as an in-group way.
So for your kids, empathy
is absolutely appropriate.
My God, you better feel their
pain 'cause they are you,
but for a population you
don't empathize with them.
And the charities have
known this for years.
They don't show you a
population of starving people.
They show your help can help this child,
you know, Sally in Sub Saharan Africa,
look at her and then you go, absolutely.
'Cause that's how we're wired.
- Interesting.
- [Dr. Z] It's really interesting.
- I think that's really right.
But I think compassion in the sense
that you mean it exactly
the right thing here.
So we have to understand.
So like the scientific evidence
says that the teachers
face about as much risk
as other professions doing their work,
not from the kids again,
from other staff members.
But you act on that.
You said, okay, well,
given that that's the case,
so let's structure the workplace
to reduce that risk as much as we can.
What they're doing is a
vital function for the kids,
for society at large, they
are absolutely essential.
So they're, they're taking a risk.
We should honor them for taking that risk.
Just like we honor the
doctors that have come in
or the nurses that have come in
to come to care for their patients.
They're not doing something
as less vital than that.
- It's funny 'cause you'll see memes
where it was like,
teachers will say, we
didn't sign up for this.
And the nurses will say, neither did we.
We didn't sign up to
put ourselves at risk,
but we do our essential job.
Someone wrote a nurse wrote
an Op-ed and it shouldn't,
it's not a real contest
between who's the bigger martyr
it's the idea is that they're both honored
as absolutely essential.
And it's tough because you
do feel for people too,
who are at risk and
that's why it's nuanced.
And it's something you
even opened the show with
where you said you're heartbroken
about the suicide statistics.
That's because what you're showing is love
in the face of suffering.
Love and concern in the face of suffering
will lead you to feel that way, right.
Because you go, I can't, this is terrible.
So let's have the discourse
from a place of compassion
and the way that you've been treated,
I think is just abhorrent
because that's not a
compassionate response.
It's let's talk if we
disagree, that's fine.
And then we can have the argument,
but why are we vilifying people?
- Yeah, I don't have much to complain.
I actually have been
fortunate in many ways.
And actually it's been interesting
from a professional point of view
to be able to contribute at all to this.
In many ways gratifying that
I've had something to say,
but I completely agree
with the spirit of it.
Let's look at the data.
Let's make decisions that understand
that we're making decisions
that affect the lives of everybody,
not just the people with COVID
and COVID is not the only public
health danger that we face.
And that there are trade offs,
there's risks on all sides.
There's not a safe
option where we can say,
and so I think like
cheap rhetorical tricks,
like, oh, you only care about the economy.
You don't care about lives.
I think for the most part
it's aimed at shutting
down just conversation
as opposed to having serious conversation.
- Yeah, I agree, I agree.
Man, was there anything
else you wanna talk about?
- I think we covered it, thank you.
- Oh my gosh,
this was such a enjoyable
conversation for me
because it allows an airing
of this kind of side of the conversation
that I just don't think we're
getting in a clear eyed way.
So if mainstream media does
it, it's politicized by Fox.
If the left does it, it's
politicized by the media,
I'm trying to create a space here
and hopefully we can
have more conversations
where we just get out some
interesting information
in a clear way.
- Well, I'm really honored
to be able to talk with you.
And actually it's been really interesting
to be able to have this
conversation as open.
I think there's stuff
we probably disagree on a little,
I don't know what time.
- Sure.
- But I think having a space
where you can actually do that,
I think all of science
should be like that.
- I 100% agree.
So we're gonna try increasingly
to use the space for that kind of good.
Guys like, I mean, this was a conversation
you can disagree I want you to,
I want you to leave comments.
I want you to leave ad
hominem attacks out of it,
if you can,
let's try to use our critical thinking.
Do me a favor Just share this thing.
It'll be on a podcast.
It'll be on my website zdoggmd.com.
It'll be on YouTube.
It'll be on Facebook.
Ultimately what we do
is we make a little square
out of it and caption it
and put it on Facebook
too so you can read along.
The transcript will be
out in a couple of days.
I love you guys.
Please stay well.
Please let stop stifling
discussion and having it.
Dr. Bhattacharya I mean,
what a real thrill,
please come back.
- I'd love to.
- Awesome, awesome and we out peace.