My name is Brad and I'm a conservative Republican
Last summer I happened to come across a video on the Internet about the World Trade Center demolition on September 11th
As a kind of demolition hobbyist, I downloaded it and watched it
The title was Painful Deceptions, by a guy called Eric Hufschmid
The video made me very angry
I was determined to prove the maker of the video wrong
I purchased videos about 9/11 from CBS and PBS Nova, including one made by the Naudet brothers
These were considered the official videos
After watching them carefully, and after researching thousands of websites and archives on the Internet
literally not sleeping for an entire week
I realized that official story, not Eric Hufschmid's Painful Deceptions, was unprovable,
unsubstantiated, absolutely wrong
What you are about to see is information you should already know
Our news reporters, government and media should have made all this material available to every one of us
Ask yourself why you've never seen it on TV
This is as close as we can get to the base of the World Trade Center
You can see the firemen assembled here, the police officers, FBI agents
911 Mysteries
Part 1: Demolitions
The Myth
On September 11th, we learned that four passenger planes were hijacked and taken radically off course
Within an hour, two of the planes had flown into the enormous steel towers of the World Trade Center,
creating fires and eventually toppling them
Dazed by the news, the American public soon believed
the fires in the towers had burned so hot they caused the steel frames of the buildings to give way
A myth developed,
fed by official sources through the media to a bewildered audience
Elements of the myth: the impact of the airplanes, gallons of burning jet fuel, steel melting,
the buildings failing and suddenly imploding
In a mere 10 seconds, 110 stories hurtled earthward,
pulverizing into dust
Right from the start, on the street itself, the official story was born
..come out of nowhere and just reamed right into the side of the Twin Tower, exploding through the other side,
and then I witnessed both towers collapse, one first and then the second, mostly due to structural failure because the fire was just too intense
The myth bled into the FEMA report and was echoed by the experts
It was the combination of impact load doing great damage to the building, followed by the fire, that caused collapse
Gene Corley, PhD., American Society of Civil Engineers
John Skilling and Les Robertson were the structural engineers who designed the streamlined steel frames of the Twin Towers in the 1960s
Because a wayward army bomber flew into the Empire State Building in 1945,
the towers were built with skyscraper crashes in mind
The airplane we were envisioning was the largest airplane of its time,
flying slowly and low, lost in the fog
We designed the buildings to take the impact of the Boeing 707, hitting the building at any location
[Official story] But the aircraft that hit the towers was a Boeing 767, heavier than a 707,
fueled for a transcontinental flight and traveling fast
Boeing 707 and 767 are comparable
The maximum take-off weight of a fully loaded 707 is almost 334,000 pounds
As airplanes only carry the fuel load they need, the smaller-model 767s that struck the towers
were not, in actuality, maximally fueled
or close to their maximum take-off weight
As for the heat of the fires, listen to the radio communications of these New York City firemen:
78 floor, we've got two isolated pockets of fire
We should be able to knock it down with two lines. Radio that, 78th floor
Isolated pockets of fire. Two water lines to knock them down
FEMA's Executive Summary relays that much of the fuel in the planes (jet-grade kerosene) was consumed by the initial fireballs,
and the following few minutes of fire
It then tells us:
[Official story] The burning jet fuel spread between floors and ignited the building's contents,
causing more fire and generating heat
This was somehow enough to bring down the towers' 47-column steel core,
236 exterior columns and thousands of steel trusses, all at the same time
Watch the towers smoking in the aftermath of the plane strikes
If you have ever tried to light a wood fire,
you will know that smoking logs tell you the fire is NOT burning successfully
Smoke is the sign of an oxygen-starved fire
The Twin Towers stood for over an hour, smouldering but not flaming
During that time, thousands of people were evacuated by way of the stairwells
Others, trapped by debris, stood in the smoke-filled windows and signaled for help
In fact, the towers did what they were built to do
The building was designed to have a fully loaded 707 crash into it
That was the largest plane at the time
I believe that the building probably could sustain multiple impacts of jetliners
because this structure is like the mosquito netting on your screen door
This intense grid
And the jet plane is just a pencil puncturing that screen netting,
it really does nothing to the screen netting
The towers were built to withstand 140-mile-an-hour (220 km/h) gusts produced by winter storms
Anyone in them on a windy day could feel them swaying
The single impact of a jetliner was no more of a blow than the continued battering of a hurricane
I was just putting my stuff away and all of the sudden we heard a loud crash
and the building started shaking, kind of moving like a wave..
New Yorkers were stunned, one hour later, when the first tower fell
[Official story] To the best of my knowledge, the considerations of the fuel in the airplane, in terms of an explosion or a great fire
! was not considered !
We were not responsible for that aspect of the design
Imagine:
building expressly for airplane impact, but never thinking of the fuel
Steel Buildings
Never before in the history of the world has a steel building collapsed due to fire
I have not seen until recently a protected steel structure that has collapsed in a fire
Jonathan Barnett, PhD., Worcester Polytechnic Institute
True infernos have raged hot and long in steel-framed buildings,
but not one of the buildings ever came down
In 1975, the World Trade Center's North Tower suffered a nighttime fire
that flamed for three hours, spreading vertically from floor to floor
It burned twice as long as the fires of 9/11, without even a hint of a building collapse
In February 2005, the Windsor Tower in Madrid, a skyscraper undergoing reconstruction,
sustained a 20-hour fire
This is what was left
a standing building strong enough to support a crane
Compare a 20-hour inferno to 90 minutes of smoke
Why are buildings made of steel ?
Strong, light and flexible, steel frames offer many advantages over wood and concrete,
especially where skyscrapers are concerned
Steel makes big buildings relatively light, with tremendous load-bearing capacity
The upper floors won't crush the floors beneath them, and steel holds up better to weather and fire
WTC Design and Construction
Most skyscrapers are built on steel or concrete frames,
which is a grid of columns and beams that goes all the way through the building
The World Trade Center was different
It was what engineers call a "tube structure"
It was a very very strong mesh of steel that surrounded the exterior.
Inside, there was the core
A rectangle of 47 columns made of 4-inch-thick steel at the base,
thinning with increasing height,
the cores combined might with ingenuity,
anchoring the towers and allowing them to flex
Look at the size of this steel
Solid, pre-fabricated floor assemblies,
welded metal floor pans placed on top of trusses both welded AND bolted to the vertical frames
[Official story] This rock-like steel grid gave way because fire warped the trusses, causing the bolts to fail
As the trusses sagged and fell, the floors dropped with them
In its 2002 documentary "Why the Towers Fell," PBS creates a video model
Once the trusses failed, the floors they were holding cascade down
with a force too great to be withstood
The result is what's called a progressive collapse,
as each floor pancakes down on the one below
What remains standing ? The tall, indestructible core
Why does PBS fail to explain the complete disappearance of the Twin Tower's cores ?
The official story's central thesis is based on heat, temperatures high enough to weaken steel
But people in the towers did not report such heat
Think about it
Neither steel, concrete, nor glass can burn
So what, in those buildings, could have burned to make such heat ?
How do these firefighters describe the collapse of the North Tower ?
We started running.. Floor by floor, it started popping out..
It was as if they had detonators. Yeah, detonators, yeah.. As if they planned to take down a building. Boom, boom, boom, boom, boom !
All the way down. I was watching it and running
And others give similar descriptions
At 10:30 I tried to leave the building, but as soon as I got outside I heard a second explosion,
and another rumble and more smoke and more dust
And then a fire marshall came in and said we had to leave because if there was a third explosion, this building might not last
..like, it sounded like gunfire, BANG-BANG-BANG-BANG
And then all of the sudden three big explosions..
..started walking down the stairs to the 8th floor, big explosion, blew us back into the 8th floor
Do you know if it was an explosion or if it was a building collapse ?
To me, it sounded like an explosion
Chief Albert Turi told me that he was here after the events that took place this morning
He tried to get his men out as quickly as he could,
but he said that there was another explosion which took place
And then an hour after, there was another explosion in one of the towers here
So, according to his theory, he thinks there were actually devices that were planted in the building
Reports of bombs in the buildings, explosions
CBS reporter Carol Marin:
I was coming toward the World Trade Center looking for CBS crews,
and asked a firefighter if he saw any
All of the sudden there was a roll, an explosion,
and we could see coming at us a ball of flame stories high
Listen to the sound of a large explosion right before the South Tower begins to fall
This is as close as we can get to the base of the World Trade Center
You can see the firemen assembled here, the police officers, FBI agents
Sound reaches us after what we see (in storm we see lightning before sound of thunder)
If the BOOM we just heard was the sound of the building collapsing, it would FOLLOW the collapse
Instead, the BOOM is heard before
Ho, whoa, whoa, bring it back
Explosion
then the collapse
Facts about Steel
Let's consider the characteristics of steel
Steel is an alloy of iron, containing added carbon for flexibility, workability and strength
In the days of old, blacksmiths heated iron till it was red and pounded it for hours to form it
Horseshoes, knife blades and plowshares were typical creations
Steel was introduced in the mid-1800s
and by the end of the century, with the advent of the blast furnace, found widespread commercial use
A blast furnace is known as a controlled environment. High temperatures are reached as oxygen is pumped into a closed space
How and when does steel melt ?
Steel melts at temperatures of 2750°F (1510°C) and above,
attained ONLY in a blast furnace or when a powerful incendiary such as thermite is used
Steel, or any substance that is burned,
will never become hotter than the temperature of the fire or heat applied to it
An open-air hydrocarbon fire reaches a maximal temperature of some 1200°F (650°C)
in a "dirty" or uncontrolled burn
characterized by red-orange flames
Red-orange flames are what we saw on September 11th
Even the fireball caused by the plane strike was red-orange
A controlled burn falls between a dirty burn (like a fireplace)
and a controlled environment (the blast furnace)
A controlled burn employs a regulated mix of air and fuel
An example being your gas stove or the engine in your car
You can fire up your gas stove all day long,
making soup, roasting a duck or simmering a stew
Made of steel, your stove will not melt
and nor will your pots and pans
This is a kerosene heater, designed for use in any ordinary house
The heater runs on jet-grade kerosene, contained in this tank
Made of steel, the heater can operate all night and all day
The kerosene fumes ignite and burn inside it (1800°F/980°C),
never causing even the smallest part of this heater to weaken or melt
Yet we were led to believe that these tremendous buildings, framed in steel and surfaced in aluminum,
totally collapsed from small, scattered fires and 90 minutes of smoke
Take note of these hurtling beams,
thrown laterally outward as the tower comes to earth
Would fire have the strength to eject such huge hunks of metal ?
MIT engineering professor Thomas Eagar's 2001 paper
is officially considered the academic standard for explaining the World Trade Center collapses
In it he tells us that steel loses half its strength at 650°C
and that the fires that day did not get much hotter than this
He stresses, however, that the fires did not burn evenly
It was the uneven temperatures that caused the steel to deform and some of the floors to fail
These falling floors brought down the whole building
While it was impossible for the fuel-rich, diffuse-flame fire to burn at a temperature high enough to melt the steel,
its quick ignition and intense heat caused the steel to lose at least half its strength and to deform, causing buckling or crippling
This weakening and deformation caused a few floors to fall, while the weight of the stories above them crushed the floors below, initiating a domino collapse
In plain language, straight from MIT: Fires not hot enough to melt steel
Uneven fires deformed some of the steel
Some floors fell – smashing the entire building
Dr. Eagar ... what happened to the core ?
Building Collapses
What do falling buildings look like ?
What do demolitions look like ?
We are seeing typical implosions,
characterized by gutting a building's base and then pulling it into itself
Computer-controlled sequencing fires the explosives in a rapid wave
Notice the jets of shooting concrete,
the flashes, the pops, the caving of the buildings as they fall into their footprint
The tremendous, billowing clouds of dust
Now let's look at the collapse of the Twin Towers:
We are seeing explosions, rather than implosions, a first in demolition history.
A sequenced rumble becomes a roar as debris is thrown outward
The damage is not contained
Even the windows are blown from neighborhood buildings
What kind of energy enabled this ?
Would fire hurl metal and concrete sideways into the air ?
Here, a 600,000-pound (270 tons) chunk of steel, twice the weight of a Boeing airliner
was flung 400 feet (120m), wedging itself deep into Three World Financial Center on Vesey Street
A FEMA photographer taking pictures of Ground Zero wondered why so MANY steel beams were jutting from neighborhood buildings
What shot pieces of the towers all the way across the street ?
In April 2006 New Yorkers were distressed to learn that bone fragments - human remains from 9/11
had been found on the roof of the nearby Deutsche Bank building
And how in God's name did those fragments get there ?
It surprised me that there was still bone fragments, or human remains, that had not been discovered
How is it possible that after five years they are finally looking on the rooftop of the Deutsche building ? I mean, that's crazy
And bone fragments less than a centimeter long
How could they be so small ?
So much to be explained
Why did the South Tower fall first, when it was the second tower to be hit ?
Watch the top third of Tower 2 leaning outward, about to topple
Then, suddenly, it disintegrates in mid-air
What causes this giant slab of steel and concrete to turn into dust before our eyes ?
Watch both buildings collapsing straight down - directly into the path of most resistance
which is all the floors and all the mass of the building itself
The World Trade Center Towers came down in approximately 10 seconds
Seismic data from Columbia University puts the North Tower collapse at about 8 seconds
and the South Tower at approximately 10
Lynn Simpson, a survivor from the 89th floor of the North Tower, describes the sight:
And I saw the Trade Center literally collapse in upon itself floor by floor by floor
and it took seconds for it to happen
It was a massive building, and it just pancaked
10 seconds
These are 110-story buildings, coming to earth at free-fall speed
The rate at which an object drops through air
The lower floors would need to give way completely as the floors above them fell
Can a person walk through a closed door as quickly and smoothly as one that is open ?
A 10-second collapse means the upper floors encountered no resistance from the undamaged floors beneath them.
Watch the demolition wave rushing straight down
Here the South Tower is half its original height,
but wreckage from the upper collapse has not yet fallen this far
We are watching a demolition moving faster than gravity itself,
a building bursting into powder from top to bottom
Here, the core of the North Tower finally gives up
700 remaining feet (200m) of giant steel columns, among the strongest ever erected
What force acts upon the core to make it all of a sudden disappear ?
Eric Hufschmid, author of the book “Painful Questions,” is a metal-cutting software engineer
The floors of the World Trade Center towers were a three-dimensional
mesh of steel beams
You have to keep in mind now, the floor is about an acre in size (65x65m),
there are thousands of joints all over it
In order for the floor to fall down, thousands of joints would have to break simultaneously
So then, if you look at the speed at which this came down, less then ten seconds
You blink your eye and thousand of joints just popped somehow
The only way you can explain that is with explosives
They had to have had explosives placed all over the floors at the primary joints
Then that would explain how all of the joints broke at such a rapid rate
The debris was crashing from one floor to the next
Debris cannot crash through steel and concrete floors as fast as it falls through the air
and there was no slowing
Explosives had to be breaking the joints ahead of the falling rubble,
which is why the top half starts off collapsing slowly and then it starts picking up speed
This is a pancake collapse:
Why don't we see piles of floors at Ground Zero ?
And paper blown everywhere
Wouldn't a pancake collapse have trapped the contents inside ?
What blew this paper all over New York ?
If you were to drop a billiard ball from the top of the Twin Towers, it would hit the ground in just over 9 seconds,
the average time it took for the towers to fall
Helped by gravity and falling through air, the ball will gain speed
The calculation for a "pure" pancake collapse of 110 stories, with each floor pulverizing to get out of the way, is 96 seconds.
In the real world, with the floors creating resistance,
a pancake collapse would lose speed - never would it gain speed
Pre-collapse
Sub-basement explosions
The airplanes struck the towers high above the ground
But down in the lobby of the North Tower, marble facing flew off the walls, the windows shattered, all the glass blown out
Guy from the Port Authority told them the damage was somewhere above the 78th floor
All you had to do was look around
It was obvious, something had happen right there in the lobby.
And you just saw, all the windows were blown out. The lobby looked like the plane hit the lobby
Like the plane hit the lobby
What caused so much wreckage in the lobby ?
William Rodriguez, a maintenance employee at the World Trade Center and the last human being to exit the towers alive, describes a giant blast below his building
..and all of the sudden we heard an explosion. It was a huge explosion that came from under my feet,
meaning that it came from the sub-levels between B2 and B3, and there was a huge explosion at the top of the building
You could hear the difference from the bottom and all the way through the top
The one from the top, which was actually seconds after,
was heard very far away
The one at the basement was pretty loud, and you felt your actual feet moving with the floor
The tremor that is sent through the floors, the walls cracked and the false ceiling totally collapsed,
and that's when a person name Felipe David came running into our office saying: Explosion! Explosion! Explosion!
And when I saw him, he has all his skin pulled from under his armpits and missing pieces on his face
An explosion deep down in the tower, before the plane crash 95 floors above
Others lived to report enormous explosions below the towers
Construction worker Phillip Morelli was in North Tower Sub-basement 4 at the time of the first plane strike
I go downstairs. The foreman tells me to go to remove the containers
As I'm walking by the main freight car of the building, in the corridor, that's, that's when I got blown
I mean the impact of the explosion, of whatever happened, it threw me to the floor, and that's when everything starting happening
"Blown to the floor". Let's hear what happened next
I was racing, I was going towards the bathroom. All of the sudden I
opened the door, I didn't know it was a bathroom
and all of the sudden a big impact happened again, and all of the ceiling tile was falling down, the light fixtures were falling, swinging out of the ceiling
and I come running out the door, and everything, the walls were down, and now I start running towards the parking lots
There was a lot of smoke down there. There was a lot of people screaming. People came with us, running up the ramps
Philip then ran underground to the South Tower
You know, you gotta go clear across the hole from One to Two World Trade Center, you know, I mean that's the way you got to run,
and then all of the sudden it happen all over again
Something else hit us to the floor. Right in the basement you felt it. Wall were caving in, everything that was going on
I know people that got killed in the basement, I know people that got broken legs in there, in the basement
People got reconstructive surgery because the walls hit them in the face
Engineer Mike Pecoraro in the sixth sub-basement, found the parking garage and machine shop reduced to rubble
Pre-collapse interior blasts
Rescue firemen and civilians spoke of hearing explosions throughout the towers
Firefighter Lou Cacchioli told People Magazine
that as he and others evacuated workers, bombs were going off inside the building
Explosions stalled elevators and filled entire floors with smoke and debris
I got an eyewitness that said there was explosion on floor Seven Eight, Seven Eight
We've just had another explosion
Warren Street because of the secondary explosion,
we've got numerous people covered with dust from the secondary explosion
We've got another explosion in the tower 10-13, 10-13 (This code = Fire Marshall Needs Assistance, Urgent Assist by NYPD)
We have a bigger explosion and what looks like a complete collapse, surrounding the entire area
I was involved in a secondary explosion..
William Rodriguez, helping the firefighters, reports blasts within the North Tower well before it fell
As I went up, I remember listening to small explosions on the upper floors,
and these small explosions were not coming from the area of the impact it was coming from lower floors
And when the second plane hit the South Tower:
We heard “boom.” When we heard BOOM, inside our building, the North tower, we heard "pop-pop-pop-pop-pop-pop",
and on the security radio we heard, “We lost 65! We lost 65!” meaning the 65th floor collapsed
And as we went down the stairwells you could hear the actual collapsing inside the building
You heard rumble. You heard the cracking of the walls. I mean pieces falling, right next to us, of the actual building
Pre-collapse ground-level explosions
What happened at the base of the towers just before they came down ?
Smoke appeared at street level
This video was shot from New Jersey
An explosion is heard as white smoke rises at the base of the building
Watch the camera shake on its tripod as a large energy source rocks the ground
Nine seconds later, the North Tower falls
I heard like an explosion and then a cracking type of noise, and then it sounded like a freight train,
rumbling and picking up speed. I looked up and I saw it coming down
Firefighter Timothy Julian
As I came out of the North Tower, everything started trembling under my feet like an earthquake
The only thing I saw was a firetruck. I ran towards the firetruck and slid right under, when the building started to collapse right under the firetruck
William Rodriguez, WTC janitor
Pre-and mid-collapse explosions
Across the Hudson River, Richard Siegel was filming an astonishing day
The sound meter of Richard's camera caught something very significant
Adjusted for the distance involved (as sound travels more slowly than what we see),
the camera registered multiple explosions in the towers
Here is the South Tower record:
Then the building fell
Squibs - visible explosions
Let's look carefully at the collapse itself
Notice the puffs of concrete issuing from the sides of the building well ahead of the collapse wave
Called "squibs" in demolition language,
these are actual explosives – charges firing visibly through the exterior
as gravity pulls the building down
Here are more:
Shattering from the top, engulfed by banana-peel plumes,
these were no ordinary implosions
The Twin Towers each consisted of three multi-story buildings set on top of one another
To sustain the weight of so many floors, the “sky lobbies” had to be extra-heavily reinforced
Watch a big squib coming from the sky-lobby band
Shockwave
A powerful blast produces what is called a "shockwave"
Explosions generate extremely high compressional waves that exceed the limits of surrounding air and space,
creating a violent force
When the debris starting coming down I was right in the shadow of the South tower
I was less then a hundred yards (100m) away
Everybody saw the video, over and over again, of that cloud chasing people down the street
It was like a tornado
It was like being hit by a wave at the beach,
but the wave was intense, it was hot, it was noisy
It was like getting hit in the back by gravel, rocks, like somebody had picked up handfuls of rocks and was just throwing them at you
And the noise just kept coming and coming,
and one second I was running, and the next second I was flying
I had no control over my feet, no choice as to what direction I was going
I was in the air, and it seemed like I was being followed by this tornado
tornado of darkness
The South Tower fell first
This is the shockwave blast as it rocks the tower next door
Pyroclastic surge
As the buildings fell, they darkened Manhattan,
filling the air with billowing clouds of dust and ash
What produces these huge, scudding cauliflower-like masses of slowly moving dust ?
True, a 110-story building has just been reduced to a million tons of rubble
But is there anything in our experience we can compare it to ?
A volcano
The US Geological Survey website provides us with a definition of a pyroclastic flow,
as a ground-hugging avalanche of hot gas and debris
The rising gas chimney is clearly visible in this photo of the North Tower implosion,
with pyroclastic flows between buildings
The cauliflower shape of the debris cloud is a telltale sign of pyroclastic flows
generated by massive explosions, typical of volcanic eruptions and controlled demolitions
A pyroclastic surge can even flow over water
as hot gases carry dust created by explosive energy
Here, the South Tower implosion creates a pyroclastic surge, moving out over the Hudson River
A volcanic eruption produces exactly the same thick, scudding ash - heavy with debris,
hugging the ground as it flows out from a tremendous internal explosion
The slurry walls
On the southern tip of Manhattan, surrounded by water,
huge retaining walls were built below the World Trade Center
to hold back the ocean and Hudson River
The "bathtub" as it was called, held 7 levels of parking garages,
maintenance rooms and the New Jersey path train station
After September 11th, the 3-foot-thick slurry walls were found to have shifted up to 18 inches (45cm) inward
These walls are coming in. These wall hold back the river,
so if these wall cave in, this place is going to get flooded out be the river
Let's think about this
A pancake collapse should have left the foundations in place
They had always borne the weight of 110 floors
But something happened in the sub-basements to disrupt them
All the collapse had gone down to track level,
so we had 60, 70 feet (20m) of wall totally unsupported
What kind of force could have dislodged so many stories deep underground ?
Molten metal
The pile itself seemed to have a life of its own
It spewed fire when we dug into it
The ground continued to burn
Les Robertson publicly reported that 3 weeks after the collapse, live fires burned and molten metal still flowed underground
You see how this is still smoking ?
That's from the fire still burning
Eight weeks later we still got fires burning
Steel-toed boots is one of the biggest things
Out still on the rubble it's still I believe 1100°F (600°C)
The guy's boots just melt within a few hours
In November 2005, physics Professor Steven Jones of Brigham Young University
published a 25-page treatise on the collapse of the Twin Towers and Building 7,
applying the laws of physics to the official story
From an interview on MSNBC:
As we read in the FEMA report, it says here, and I put this in my paper, of course
The best hypothesis, which is the only one they looked at, fire, "has only a low probably of occurrence."
"Further investigation and analysis are needed to resolve this issue". And I agree with that.
I'm sorry that we are out of time, and I'm not sure that you have fully..
Whoa! One other thing I want to mention.. Okay, if you could hit it, just really quickly
Okay, here we go. Molten metal in the basements of all three buildings (WTC1,2 a WTC7)
And yet all scientists now reasonably agree that the fires were not sufficiently hot to melt the steel
So what is this molten metal ?
It's direct evidence for the use of high temperature explosives, such as thermite
Thermite produces molten iron as an end product
Okay, we appreciate your coming on,
even if I don't understand your theories. We appreciate your trying to explain it. Thanks
Professor Jones barely got in his mention of thermite
An incendiary used by the military,
thermite is a compound of iron oxide and aluminum
which when ignited, sustains an extreme heat reaction,
creating molten iron
In just 2 seconds, thermite can reach temperatures over 4500°F (2500°C),
quite enough to liquefy steel
This is thermite melting the engine of a car
We know that open-air fires cannot burn hot enough to melt steel
But metal had melted at the base of the towers
The second product of a thermite reaction is aluminum oxide visible as white smoke
Was thermite used in conjunction with explosives on September 11th ?
Watch this very bright substance pouring from the 81st floor of the South Tower
And white smoke appeared at the base of the building
Would this be aluminum oxide, the byproduct of a thermite reaction ?
Appendix C of the FEMA Report describes sulfur residues on the World Trade Center steel
The New York Times called this the "deepest mystery" of all
Sulfur slightly lowers the melting point of iron
and iron oxide and iron sulfide had formed on the surface of the structural steel
Sulfur used with thermite is called thermate,
producing even faster results
The demolition industry
Let's look at what happens in the demolition industry
Taking down large structures requires preparation
Powerful explosives and heavy equipment are used in advance
to weaken the foundation and bottom sections of a building
before additional explosives and gravity bring the rest of it down
The words of a senior blaster:
We blow the basement, all the columns in the basement
Then we crack it up at the top to get it started
We go every other floor all the way down
Every explosive has a timer on it, that's why it's controlled
When the columns go, each floor goes down and impacts the one below and keeps going
Here's what demolition experts use in steel-framed buildings
The linear shaped charge
It's a chevron-shaped or v-shaped charge that you can focus at a specific target,
and it's lethal. It generates around 3 million pounds per square inch pressure (200 tons per square cm)
at a speed depending on the explosive inside the shaped charge, in excess of 27000 feet per second (8km per sec)
Besides the unfathomably powerful shaped charge, blasters have a lot of tricks
There are over a thousand different types of explosives,
different because they detonate at varying speeds
This is detonating cord, and this burns at about 21000 feet per second (6 km/s)
With the use of delays, we can control pretty much where the debris lands
We can control vibration, we can control noise levels. Timing a delays are the keys to just about everything in our business
And what is the result ?
The thing that pleases me is the fragmentation and the control. When you take a building,
break it up into millions of pieces and put it into its basement,
as artfully as we do, and it works just like clockwork
9/11 WTC Demolitions
Were the underground explosions intended to blow out the Twin Towers' basements
followed by blasts heard inside the buildings of shaped charges slicing the core ?
Demolition pre-weakening usually takes place well in advance of the final blast,
but at the World Trade Center critical prep work might have had to occur in a very compressed time frame
in the panicked aftermath of the plane strikes
These core columns were discovered after the collapse
The angled cut occurs exactly in the manner that shaped charges slice through steel beams
to control the way they fall
Notice the hardened once-liquid metal
Was thermite used with the shaped charge ?
The job of the shaped charge is to cut steel H-beams
The way we do this is by cutting the beam at an angle
which, through a series of beams cut at the same angle, will tend to make the building shift over and walk
Let's look at the rubble of two 110-story buildings brought to the ground
In a 7-story crater, lie nearly 2 million tons of debris
Had the basements not been blown out, where would 2 million tons have gone ?
Heaped on the ground, ready to slide and spill
The art of controlled demolition
Remember the pre-collapse and mid-collapse explosions caught by Richard Siegel's camera on the Jersey shore ?
Were these the blasts that took the out core and upper basements just before the final crumble
a mind-boggling sequence of computer-controlled delays
that blew the exo-skeleton  pulverized the concrete
to bring the whole structure rolling to the ground
Was this the story of that day ?
1) Pre-collapse sub-basement explosions (lower basements and substructure)
2) Pre-collapse interior blasts (endo-skeleton, cutting core columns)
3) Pre-collapse ground-level explosions (upper basements and lower supports)
4) Top-level collapse initiation (cracking the top)
5) Mid-collapse squibs (shooting sections ahead of collapse)
6) Final time-delayed roll (exo-skeleton and pulverization)
Who knew ?
Some people appear to have known the imminent future on that fateful day
FEMA had arrived in New York on Monday night, ready for a bio-terror drill
Spokesman Tom Kenney:
To be honest with you, we arrived on late Monday night (10.sept - day before attacks!) and went into action on Tuesday morning,
and not until today did we get a full opportunity to work the entire site, other than this part of Church and Day to which we were deployed
And Rudy Guliani, Mayor of New York, tells ABC that he was aware the towers would be coming down
What's going on now is a massive rescue effort
And do you believe it is hundreds or thousands ?
I really don't want to say right now,
but I think it's going to be a horrible number
I saw people jumping out of the World Trade Center, I saw some of the firefighters who I know going into the building,
And we were in a building in which we were trapped for 10, 15 minutes,
and we set up headquarters at 75 Barclay Street which was right there
with the Police Commissioner, the Fire Commissioner, the head of Emergency Management
and we were operating out of there when we were told the World Trade Center was going to collapse
..WTC was going to collapse!
Similarly, Larry Silverstein, new leaseholder of the World Trade Center,
regretfully declared that a decision was made to pull Building 7 by the end of the day,
the last structure added to the World Trade Center complex
Let's hear Mr Silverstein's actual words, delivered for our benefit in the 2002 PBS documentary America Rebuilds
I remember getting a call from the fire department commander,
telling me they were not sure they we going to be able to contain the fire,
and I said: you know, we've had such a terrible loss of life,
maybe the smartest thing to do is pull it
and they made that decision to pull,
and then we watched the building collapse
Blast, shoot, blow and pull are terms used in the demolition industry
to refer to bringing down buildings, bridges and other structures
Because I actually blew the hospital down that I was born in
Originally we had figured to shoot it, let it drop straight down
Then, watch Demolition Dynamics attempt a big blast
And from Ground Zero's own post-disaster wrecking crew
By mid-December, the Department of Design and Construction had leveled World Trade Center buildings 4 and 5
Oh, we are getting ready to pull Building 6
Silverstein, a commercial real-estate tycoon with international political connections,
acquired a 99-year lease on the World Trade Center complex in the spring of 2001
Throughout the summer, he reworked the insurance policies on his new property, making sure that it was covered for acts of terrorism
Explicit in the lease agreement
was Silverstein's right to rebuild the complex if it were destroyed
After 9/11, Mr Silverstein fought in his insurers court to obtain double his policy limits for the destruction of his property,
maintaining that the double hijacking constituted two disasters caused by terrorists, not just one
He won, and was awarded over $7 billion
a magnificent return on his original $15 million investment Silverstein
My first reaction is to think about the families  of those people, the tragedy, the magnitude of it
However, I firmly believe that we should rebuild
WTC Building 7
Just in the last few seconds another building, WTC 7, one of the buildings in support of the WTC towers, has collapsed
WTC 7, functioning as the command center for the complex,
housed giant diesel backup and oxygen systems, the Mayor's protected emergency bunker,
and offices for the CIA, Secret Service, Department of Defense and Securities
and Exchange Commission
Its other tenants were insurance companies, brokerages and banks
No plane hit Building 7
But at 17:20 p.m. on September 11th, it collapsed in a heap on the ground
Some damage to Building 7 is said to have been caused by debris from Tower 1
Though this New York Times article tells us Building 7 burned like a giant torch,
the only visuals that exist are of unidentified smoke
and a few small fires
Compare this to the wallops sustained by
WTC 3
WTC 4
WTC 5 and 6
Positioned right below the towers, damage to the surrounding WTC buildings was infinitely worse
Still, the structures held up
But somehow rescue workers knew that Building 7 would fall
Keep an eye on that building. It'll be coming down soon
A 47-story skyscraper, Building 7 folded neatly, in 6-and-a-half seconds
A textbook descent right into its footprint
Silverstein Properties now tells us
that its owner was referring to the team of firefighters inside the building
when he spoke of the decision to pull - pulling the firemen out of harm's way
However, there were no firefighters in Building 7,
according to FEMA, NIST, and fire chief Frank Fellini
They were ordered out at 11:30 that morning
Six hours later, the building came down
Radio host Alex Jones notes the mark of a classic implosion
This is a photo taken one second into Building 7's collapse
Notice the crimp
If we look at other controlled demolitions,
we see that they first blow one of the central columns,
so the building falls in on itself
If you don't do this, the building falls outward,
and can damage surrounding structures
Building 7 had a classic crimp, or wedge
Its central column was blown out first,
so it didn't structurally damage buildings just a few feet away from it
Remember the Mayor's emergency bunker ?
Ensconced on the 23rd floor of Building 7,
it was retrofitted with super-glass, water, oxygen and its own generator
But Mayor Guiliani chose to find emergency shelter elsewhere on September 11th
Why Building 7 ?
Even the media and its experts were confused
The History Channel interviews structural engineer Ramon Gilsanz
who points out the obvious crimp and even speaks of the implosion
Engineers are not just focusing on the Twin Towers
The most disturbing structural even was not that the Twin Towers fell, but that Tower 7,
ignited by flying debris, fell due to fire alone
Building 7 was a steel-framed building, and it's the first steel-framed building
that has collapsed due to fire
The failure of the building was an implosion. It failed completely different from Towers 1 and 2, in which the floors failed first
Why Building 7 ? Let's ask the question again
As the WTC command center, was it the hub for the 9/11 plan ?
Also, in 6-and-a-half seconds, lost forever were thousands of SEC case files on corporate fraud,
including those relating to the notorious activities of giants Worldcom and Enron
A few indictments for stock fraud,
but what of the $70-billion-dollar California electricity swindle ?
It disappeared
Tower security and evacuations
No one died in the collapse of Building 7
It was vacated well in advance of its implosion
But not the Twin Towers
Why weren't police, firemen and civilians in these buildings told what to expect ?
Tragically, employees in the towers were advised to return to their offices
The announcement came on that everything was fine
Tower 1 they were evacuating, but Tower 2 was fine, and we could go back to our offices
We were about to go through the turnstile. The security guard says: Where you guys are going ?
I said: Well, I'm going home because I saw fireballs coming down
He said: No, your building is safe, it's secured. It is safer to stay in your building. Go back to your office
Stanley returned to the 81st floor then
I just happened to raise my head, looking straight towards the Statue of Liberty,
and what I say was a giant airplane coming straight towards me
The South Tower was hit between the 78th and 84th floors
Trapped on the 81st floor by crushing debris, Stanley was rescued by Brian Clark
Slowly and painfully, they made their way down a stairwell to freedom
Outside, Stanley had a feeling of uncanny prescience for what was to come
And we peered through railing up through the trees at the tower
and Stanley said: You know, I think that tower could come down
I don't know why I am telling this man, but I knew it was not over
And I said: There's no way. That's a steel structure. That's just draperies and carpets and furniture burning. You know, there's no way..
and I didn't finish my sentence when the tower started to slide
And I can still remember hearing, first of all, this boom, boom, boom - explosions
Not all were blessed with intuition or foresight
Joseph Milanowycz reached his son Greg by cell phone
Greg at that time, I could tell by his voice, was scared. He said to me:
Dad, could you get in touch with someone and tell them that there's about 20 of us on the northeast corner of the 93rd floor
Greg had been about to leave the South tower after the North Tower was attacked,
but was told it was safer to return to his desk
A couple of times he said: Why did I listen why did I listen..
Who was a director in the company that provided electronic security for the World Trade Center and Washington's Dulles Airport,
both involved in September 11th ?
None other than the president's younger brother
From 1996 to 2000, Securacom installed what was referred to as a new security system at the World Trade Center
Wirt D Walker III, a cousin of the Bush brothers, was CEO of Securacom from 1999 until 2002
Interestingly, these facts have not been made public
Was it only a security system that was added during those years,
or was it also the wiring for a long-awaited plan ?
Scott Forbes, an IT specialist in a firm that had leased space in the South Tower since its erection,
reported an unprecedented power down in his building for almost the whole weekend prior to 9/11
We were notified three weeks in advance of the power down by the Port Authority
That was relatively short notice to plan to shut down all of our banking systems
It was a big deal. It was unprecedented. We had a data center on the 97th floor, so our originating servers were all there
During that weekend, the power down meant there was no security
The doors were all open, basically
And also, the security video cameras were all off
But, there were guys in overalls carrying huge toolboxes and reels of cable walking around the building on that weekend
Employees were notified that Internet cables were being upgraded
But who were the strange workmen and what were they really doing ?
All the power was shut down
If there was a power down, that meant that everything was gone in terms of security,
in terms of access to the building, so anybody could have come there and done any kind of set-up
Having worked overtime to get his company's servers back up,
Scott took the day off on September 11th
As he watched the towers collapse from New Jersey that morning,
he was sure this had been the purpose of the mysterious weekend work
Scott notified many authorities, including the 9/11 Commission,
about the unusual and lengthy power outage,
but was ignored
Ben Fountain of Fireman's Fund spoke of unusual evacuations ordered at the Twin Towers during the weeks before September 11th
Others reported that the security alert was inexplicably lifted five days prior,
and bomb-sniffing dogs were removed
What would the dogs have discovered had they remained on duty ?
Urban renewal
Not long after the disaster, Lower Manhattan saw banners like this one
Although they were idolized as cathedral-like symbols of power and triumph that pierced the New York skyline,
the Twin Towers were big money-losers for the Port Authority of New York
They cost millions a year to equip with the basics:
electricity, water, heat, air-conditioning, sewage
and even oxygen - being airtight
As modern communications connected traders from all corners of the globe,
tenancy in the Twin Towers continued to drop
The towers presented another problem
Decades ago, their steel beams had been sprayed with fireproof asbestos
a cancer-causing material banned from use in building in the mid-1980s
Although the World Trade Center complex was given several waivers,
it was expected to clean up its act
But to remove the asbestos from every supporting beam in the Twin Towers would have been almost undoable
Quotes for this clean-up ran over a billion,
and no insurance company was willing to bear the cost
An urban renewal project of unfathomable proportions
Given the towers' issues and problems, September 11th proved an unexpected bonanza
The Trade Center was built in the 1960s to revive a rundown area of New York,
and 40 years later urban renewal could again take place
Two white elephants were removed, and a brand-new complex is in the works
The full height of the new Freedom Tower will soar to 1776 feet (533 m)
The suffocating dust that engulfed Manhattan was much more than dust
It was pulverized concrete, glass, metals, containing lead, mercury, dioxins, benzene,
and, of course, asbestos
None of that was healthy for any living thing
Today, thousands of rescue workers have developed lung cancer
and serious, permanent health conditions
And the rescue dogs continue to die
What you had was a ground-level municipal incinerator that smoldered for months
burning up the most heavily computerized building in the world
Patients have had black paste coming out of their pores
They have reported bowel movements that are blue or green, and have smelled like smoke,
despite the fact that they have not been at a fire scene for months
Only three days after September 11th, Washington instructed the EPA
to declare Manhattan safe and re-open Wall Street,
though the air remained toxic
A federal judge is blasting former head of the Environmental Protection Agency
for telling New Yorkers it was safe to return to their homes and offices near Ground Zero
soon after the 9/11 attacks
The judge called Christine Todd Whitman's actions "conscious shocking" and refuse to grant her immunity
It was documented that the White House ordered EPA to tell these lies,
to downplay the seriousness of the environmental hazards
In addition, 911 first responders who have fallen ill and applied for aid,
have been denied
Licorice steel
Asbestos plays a part in the myth of why the Twin Towers fell on September 11th
[Official story] The steel had been sprayed with lightweight fireproof foam which,
while cheaper, was much less adhesive
The New York Times has reported that the foam fell off easily,
and the Port Authority had been fixing and replacing missing sections in the months before September 11th
But even if the fireproofing had been perfectly applied,
the impact of the plane crashing into the North Tower was so powerful, it simply blew most of it off,
allowing the fire to attack the steel beneath
Once the planes hit, whatever condition it was in before the fact made no difference
because an impact would knock it off,
and the fire would have devastating effects on the steel
James Glanz, New York Times
One good smack from a jet plane and the puffs of asbestos are all blown off the steel
Would a few hundred doors slamming do the same thing ?
Here, the History Channel tells us how, due to poor fireproofing,
flames swept through the pockets between floors
[Official story] As much of the fireproofing had been dislodged on impact, the flames were attacking unprotected steel
When steel is not protected the strength reduces very fast
When you get to about 1100°F (600°C), you lose about half the strength of the steel
The fire inside the Towers may have reached 2500°F/1370°C (in reality max. 1200°F/650°C)
New York Times has reported what happened to those steel floor trusses then
The steed did heat up and became softer and softer, almost like liquish
And eventually all the steel had been weakened in this zone
40 years ago, the steel used to build the World Trade Center was certified by Underwriters Laboratories,
a global product-compliance and public-safety guardian
Let's hear a lone voice that spoke out from this enormous company
My name is Kevin Ryan and I was formerly a manager at Underwriters Laboratories
I was fired from my job five days after sending a letter to a government scientist at the NIST,
questioning the report that the NIST had recently released in October of 2004
I wrote this letter because I had serious questions about what I saw in the report
Those questions went back to September of 2001 when UL's CEO came to our location in South Bend
He told our entire staff the World Trade Center steel had been certified by UL, and he said that we should be proud of how long the buildings had stood
Over the next two years, I did some research and found some very disturbing facts,
including that the steel had been disposed of in an unprecedented manner
Once I discovered those facts, I sent a written question the UL's CEO asking him about these things
and what he was doing to protect our reputation as a company
He replied in writing to me that UL did, in fact, test the steel
He talked about the quality of the sample and how well it had performed in the tests,
and he said that our company had tested the steel, and it had done beautifully
After that, he asked me to be patient and wait for the NIST report because UL was working closely with them
I saw this report in October of 2004, and in November I sent my letter to NIST
asking for clarification
I felt it was an obligation on my part to ask the questions
since no one else seemed to care to
After the 1993 bombing, the fireproofing in both buildings was updated considerably
But when you look at the NIST report, you don't see any testing
that showed that a 767 would widely dislodge the fireproofing under any impact, let alone so far from the point of impact
So now we've been left with a new theory, which is not really a theory at all, but only a collection of vague statements
The NIST report represents what can really only be called anti-science
They started with their conclusions, and worked their way back to some leading hypothesis
When the results of the physical tests showed the temperatures were far too low to soften steel,
and that the floors could not have collapsed, and that the fireproofing could not have been widely dislodged,
the NIST ignored these results and built a black-box computer model that no one could argue with
and that they know would spit out the right answers
Today anyone who's conscious enough to know what is happening in the world knows
that most government policy is being driven by this false story
..track down and punish the perpetrators of this attack
This is being seen on Capital Hill as another Pearl Harbor
The steel, in dragon-like lengths and contortions, spoke for itself
Bent, deformed, without cracks
8 tons H-beam
I found it hard to believe that it actually bent because of the size of it
and how there's no cracks in the iron
It bent without almost a single crack in it
It takes thousands of degrees to bend steel like this
Typically you'd have buckling and tearing on the tension side,
but there's on buckling at all
Here is the meteorite
molten iron fused with concrete
Architects, engineers, people who work with steel, welders,
have just have never seen the level of destruction and the level of deformation of this material in our lives
It is true that heat expands steel
In a fire, steel members may swell and bend slightly
But this ? How could these huge tangles have been created ?
The steel below the towers had melted, at many thousands of degrees
Since metal conducts heat, were these twisted remains formed
by high temperatures wicking their way through a gridwork of steel ?
Steel deformation by heat
Explosives also deform steel
As they fire, gas pushes outward
The force of the gas can easily bend a large steel column
Two kinds of debris
Huge shattered columns that could break a truck,
combined with matter that was near pulverized
You have two 110-story office buildings
You don't find a desk, you don't find a chair, you don't find a telephone, a computer
The biggest piece of a telephone I found was half of the keypad, and it was about this big
In 1886, four gold miners lost their lives in an underground explosion
The bodies of these four men were brought to the surface in one barrel
The biggest piece recovered was part of a foot
September 11th left over 1100 bodies unaccounted for
At Ground Zero, this was found inside a length of steel
Before they seal it, workers would sometimes put there beer cans,
or newspaper, we found New York Times in a similar spot to this
Lingering questions
Secrets cannot be kept forever
Just as that newspaper from 1969 revealed itself to us decades later,
we will someday know the inside of September 11th
The reasons for the staging of such a production go far back into time
Insurance policies covered nearly everything in the World Trade Center that was destroyed
But what if certain commodities could be removed in the nick of time ?
Gold and silver held by commercial banks and the Comex exchange is said to have been stored beneath Ground Zero
This single cache, belonging to the Bank of Nova Scotia, was unearthed and made public
Was there more, and was it removed, remains a question
As Last Survivor William Rodriguez climbed the stairwell to rescue people,
he remembers a very strange thing
As I stood there on the 33rd floor, I heard very strange noises on the 34th floor
Now the 34th floor was an empty floor. A floor that did not have any kind of walls
It was a construction floor it was totally hollowed out, there was nothing there
and I heard very heavy equipment being moved around,
and it sounded like dumpsters with metal wheels being moved around and
I got scared because I knew it was an empty floor nobody was supposed to be there
As a matter of fact, not even the elevator stopped there
You have to have a special access key to open the door on the 34th floor,
so to find that there was strange noises there, I continued actually bypassing that floor
because I didn't dare to open the door on the 34th floor
Something told William Rodriguez not to mess with the 34th floor
I got scared
Yet William Rodriguez was not a man who was scared that day
He remained in a burning building against firemen's orders,
endangering his own life as he saved the lives of others
What could have been happening on the 34th floor ?
For weeks, Scott Forbes had heard similar noises on the 98th floor above him
It must have been at least four to six weeks before 9/11
It was like rebuilding work going on upstairs
The tenants, the people from Aon who had been there, were moved somewhere else
The offices were just vacant,
and there was a lot of heavy machinery building work going on
It was almost like pneumatic drills and lots of hammering
So much so that the floors were shaking, that's how noticeable it was
It was almost as if something heavy was being moved, and then it was being taken off wheels, and it was like, BOOM!
Our floor underneath literally shook
You could feel the weight above you. That was how large it was
On one occasion I opened a door to see what was going on, being nosey
When I opened the door the whole office space was empty
There was nothing there at all. It was quite bizarre
because it was just empty, completely empty, barren, nothing, zero
Not even cables hanging from the ceiling
But there'd been these heavy noises and vibrations up above
It was really strange
And the noticeable dust in the building the week before
It was probably the week leading up to 9/11
Every morning I'd come in around 7a.m., and the dust was incredible!
It was filthy. I was like the cleaners weren't cleaning. Right were the windows were, there was a sill which enclosed radiators
I was sick to death of the dust which was appearing on the window sills
It was dirty gray and very, very noticeable in that week leading up to 9/11
Where was that dust coming from ?
Gray dust Scott himself had to clean
Was it powdered cement ?
The steel columns of the Twin Towers formed an endo and exo-skeleton
Had something been placed around the edge of the building,
holes been drilled to contain it ?
Was the dust in those final days a telltale sign ?
As white elephants, the buildings were full of vacant offices
Tenants could be temporarily moved around for upgrades as Aon was, and a plan arranged to perfection
Was the strange construction that could be heard but not seen
going on all over the towers ?
Larry Silverstein took possession 6 weeks before September 11th, when the strange construction began
Were the sounds that scared William Rodriguez the last of the rats as they left a sinking ship ?
By taking a day off, Scott Forbes saved his life
This woman was not so fortunate
Calling soundlessly to people who could not help her,.. she was sacrificed on 9/11
Christopher Hanley, trapped with 100 people on the 106th floor of Tower 1
Fire Department 408 Where's the fire ?
Yeah hi, I'm on the 106th floor of the World Trade Center. We just had an explosion up here
Yeah, there's smoke and we have about a 100 people up here
Sit tight Do not leave, okay ? There's a fire or an explosion or something in the building
All right, I want you to stay where you are
Yes
Kevin Cosgrove, trapped on the 105th floor of the South Tower
Smoke – real bad – 105, Two Tower
It's really bad, it's black, it's arid
My wife thinks I'm all right I called and said I was leaving the building, I was fine,
and then - BANG!
Three of us – two broken windows
Oh, God!
Let's not forget these people, whose fate on this day was decided for them
As we know, secrets cannot be kept forever
Postscript
There are perhaps a dozen blasting companies that handle the world's major demolitions
Family-owned and widely respected, their knowledge is derived from experience
and the materials they use are conventional
WTC demolitions where highly advanced and unconventional
Explosives have always been the domain of the military, and what took place at Ground Zero
is not even fully understood by civilian blasters
The destruction of the Twin Towers and Building 7 was conducted in broad light, in a full view of news cameras and reporters,
thousands of New Yorkers, and millions who watched on live TV
Shock and awe
Fearing worse and ignorant of scientific principles, the public mind was readily manipulated
This film was made to present possibilities and raise questions. We do not have control over our airwaves
We have consigned them to large corporations who create scripted sounds bites serving as "news"
911 Mysteries gives you what the airwaves have failed to
The footage used is in some cases authorized, in other cases not, borrowed within the realm of Fair Use Doctrine and U.S. Copyright Code section 107
Use of copyrighted footage does not imply endorsement by its owners. Incorporation of comments by experts does not imply that these individuals agree with the content of this film
911 Mysteries is offered in a spirit of the American Constitution as an alternative analysis
and invitation for dialogue, a tool for awareness in the interest of public good
Ask questions. Think for yourself
Wake up, and you will make the difference
911 is a Keyhole to consciousness, if you can get through it to the other side, everything looks different
Don't be afraid
This is First Awakening. Follow your curiosity, like Alice in the rabbit hole. You are becoming free
Keep stepping forward. Share your discoveries.
You will make new friends. You are not conspiracy theorist, but part of the whole
We are all in this together
Know it, feel it, use it. This is the second awakening
Thank you for thinking
Get out there and make more consciousness
Something will happen when enough of us know
Visit 911mysteries.com. Contribute to the creation of Part 2:
Hijackers and Planes
Translated by: -YOUR NAME/NICK-, your email