The government of Iran is accusing us
of carrying out
an act of war against them.
The price of oil is spiking as a
result.
Unemployment is high and rising.
The UK economy is increasingly
fragile
and we still don't know
what's happened to Charles Flyte.
I can think of one word
we might use, Mr Speaker.
Chaos.
Hear, hear!
First of all,
let me state this quite clearly.
We have not committed
any act of war against Iran.
And on the subject of the
investigation into the plane crash,
both the Royal Navy and the United
States Navy are involved
in the search for the flight
recorder.
And without it, it's not possible
with any degree of certainty...
Mr Speaker, perhaps the Prime
Minister would care to comment
on the news just reaching us
that PetroFex is said to be on the
verge of relocating to Poland?
Order. Order!
They're citing Government hostility
and the danger of further sabotage.
And they've suspended
their offer of compensation
for the destruction at Scarrow.
But I could barely get Clark
to admit that he'd made it.
Clark claims that your ambush at the
airport demonstrates a campaign
to undermine the company's standing.
Bollocks!
All right.
You get hold of Michael Rix
at Royal Caledonian.
I'm going to freeze their fucking
assets
until we decide the level of
compensation.
Call Rix.
You mentioned sabotage?
Well, they say they've got evidence
of Dermot Matthews
making an unauthorised entry to the
plant just prior to the explosion.
Hello?
'Ellis, you're still in touch
with Jade Matthews, I believe.'
Yeah. Listen, I've just tried my luck
with the Chief of Defence Staff.
Surprise, surprise,
he didn't want to talk to me.
'What about?'
About drone fuel. What else?
'Look, about the Matthews family...'
PetroFex are claiming that her
husband may have committed an act of
sabotage.
Can you have a word with her
and see what she knows?
All right. Then you and me
are going to sit down
and have this interview for this
profile. Is that the deal?
Yes, yes. Yes, thank you.
Bye-bye.
Whose idea was it to throw the
Iranians out of their embassy?
(..The company you keep...)
Prime Minister.
General, I thought I'd made it clear
that you'd been relieved of your
post.
This will be my final briefing,
Prime Minister.
Now, it's in Afghanistan or it's in
Iran.
Which is it?
The border there has historically
been slightly ill-defined.
The topography means
that it's hard to be precise.
Can I ask why not one of you
even mentioned the proximity
of the border before?
The drones are programmed to alert us
to any territorial infringements.
Ah. Then it can't
have crossed the border?
There's...a small possibility
that the missile did.
I stress, a small possibility.
Now, it is election time in Iran.
In all probability,
the hard-liners are sabre-rattling
for electoral advantage.
They'd be fools making a claim like
that without foundation.
They'd look bigger fools if we showed them
what a real act of war looked like.
Might do the modernisers a favour -
a well-placed Cruise missile or two.
Is that why they stopped?
Because they thought they were safe?
They stopped to pray.
Because they believed
they were safe, across the border?
Is that it?
Prime Minister...
Do we have men on the ground there?
We've got Special Ops not far away,
but, um...
But they can check it out...
if it's on the wrong side
of the fucking border?
Good luck.
You'll need it, believe me.
And how's the search
for the black box going, General?
It's very deep there, Prime Minister.
The ocean.
We're going to play this down.
The Iranians will want to build it
up.
That's not going to happen.
I can't stand stainless steel.
It's like pissing in a lift.
Do that a lot, do you, Felix?
Paul Clark, um...
..he says there's nothing we can do
to stop them going to Poland.
The bank, they've...
they've frozen the assets?
Christ!
Sir Michael...
Prime Minister. My flight to Davos
is in less than two hours.
Understood. Please, take a seat.
You're in a hurry and neither of us
has anything to hide.
Please.
So, where have you put the money,
Sir Michael?
We're discussing the PetroFex
account?
You've disappeared their assets.
A multinational like PetroFex
has constant call on its holding.
Capital is a very mobile resource
these days, and for good reason.
They needed the money somewhere else
and you shifted it for them.
It's a click of the mouse,
no great strength required.
You didn't think it odd
that they would suddenly want
to expatriate
nearly three billion in sterling?
We're a bank.
We act under instruction.
We perform our fiduciary duty.
But you knew, and you personally.
This mouse click wasn't done
by Trevor in Accounts.
Your bank is the company's
biggest shareholder, am I right?
That much you can read
in the company prospectus.
And as their biggest shareholder,
you'd expect to have influence
over their major decisions?
I'm going to be late.
Do you know
who the company prospectus gives
as your bank's biggest shareholder,
Sir Michael?
Me. The British Government.
The British people.
And what we'd like you to do
is click that little mouse
and repatriate that three billion.
That's not how the world works,
Prime Minister.
Then maybe we need to address that
too.
Tom? Your alfresco summit's
got Twitter all aflutter!
Did you speak to Jade Matthews?
I'll tell you when I get back from
Davos.
'God, the whole world is in Davos.'
Well, Paul Clark is, anyway.
Well, I don't think
he's going to talk to you.
'That's not what he told me.'
So... So what did she say?
'The cab's here.'
Dermot had an accident at work
about a year ago.
He was inside one of the fuel tanks
cleaning it when it started to fill
up.
'He nearly drowned in the stuff.'
The drone fuel?
'Yeah. He wasn't a saboteur, Tom.
I can tell you that much.'
'And you're still trying to speak
to General Munnery?'
'I've got to go.
I'll speak to you soon.'
Ellis Kane. What do you know about
her?
Are you sleeping with her, Tom?
I'd love to know
where you think I get the time.
Apologies for dispensing
with the niceties.
She's the sort of woman
men like to impress.
Men like you.
Is she?
Yes. Tough, independent,
knowledgeable.
Thank you.
Like all journalists,
she only cares about one thing.
The story.
No, it's a consequence
of... Michael...listen to me!
Er, vodka and tonic, please.
Sure.
The failure of the banking system
as a whole.
Someone to shoot your mouth off to,
right?
I think you should keep your mouth
shut.
Did she give you
special dispensation, Tom?
Face time with the disreputable
Mr Fossett?
Trouble in paradise?
You're early.
I told you something once.
About Bosnia.
You did.
Just wondering...
if it's out there?
Why?
General Munnery. Things he said.
Such as?
And a journalist.
Always trouble.
Talking to him.
Well, trying to.
And you're wondering
if I've been indiscreet?
Well, you are the one
who told me about Nightlight.
In confidence.
Are you so sure about what you say
and what you don't say these days?
Excuse me?
Drop the indignation.
I don't have time for it.
Aren't we high and mighty these
days?
You keep pushing that, don't you?
Not guilty. Can I go now, please,
Prime Minister?
Maybe you should stop
feeling sorry for yourself.
You could die a bitter old drunk.
We'll have to start
charging you rent, Tony.
If you're taking up residence.
What's that?
A leggy blonde came in
in a flame-red, polka-dot dress.
Said she had a penchant
for maudlin drunks.
Hang on, sorry, I'm mistaken.
It was a brown-eyed girl,
sort of clever-looking.
Mind you, I quite like that.
I quite like a clever one.
Excuse me!
Bad influence, am I? Is that it?
Good night, Tony.
I'm not allowed
on little Tommy's trampoline?
Come on... Where?
Make a fool of me? Huh?
Ah. Yeah?
Come on, come on.
Argh!
Where is it? Where would you put...?
All this time!
Think. Think!
Come on...
Agh!
Your company put Dermot Matthews
on a bonus package,
provided he kept quiet
about an accident.
You promised to take care of his
family and assigned him a doctor,
so if he did have
any health problems,
he could keep them in-house.
Dermot went to his GP, though,
and his GP asked him
to get hold of a sample of the stuff
that he nearly drowned in.
According to Jade,
the only reason why he was there
the day of the explosion
is because
he was going to get that sample.
That's a good story.
But I can get you a better one.
What do you mean,
you can get me a better one?
"Tom Dawkins, the Army Years."
Get this lady a drink.
Aaaaarrggh!
Chaos on the Tube and gridlock
threatened on the roads this morning
as the underground networks
in London, Newcastle and Glasgow
suffer a total shutdown.
In other news this morning, the
markets opened significantly lower...
The Tube companies are saying
their bank won't sanction Oyster
transactions or card payments.
If they open the gates,
it'll be mayhem.
Which bank?
RCB.
You're joking.
Get Felix in here.
Tell Gina Hayes to pass it off
as a bank blunder
before they start to blame us.
They'll be cackling
into their croissants in Davos.
Any news from Iran?
It's gone quiet.
Small mercies.
Oh, Lee...
Ros Yelland?
What about her?
Can you get her to come and see me
before she meets
the Iranian Foreign Minister?
Hear that?
Ah, Felix.
What can you tell me?
I had a word with Sir Michael.
Really?
I was told that he was in a meeting.
He's looking into it.
How welldoyou know him?
Our wives are very good friends,
on the same charity board.
Oh.
Well, coincidence or otherwise,
I bollock him
about the PetroFex assets
and the following day,
his bank paralyses the Tube system.
Tom...
Perhaps you could have
your wife askhiswife.
You're going to have to go back
to the Bank of England, Felix.
I want them to guarantee the
underground companies' transactions,
so that we can get
the trains moving again.
You know what the Governor will say.
The Bank of England
is independent of Government.
Well, if RCB wants
to throw its weight around,
they've got to understand
that we can fight back.
But RCB will have this sorted before
the Bank of England's even out of
first gear.
Tube's up and running.
Rush hour's over.
It's a gentle poke
in the bloody ribs.
We need resolution, Tom, on Iran
and on this spat
with the Royal Caledonian.
The pound's already under pressure
and now RCB's dumping sterling.
And then what?
The Bank of England will sell
foreign reserves to prop it up.
But it won't last for ever.
Right.
Sound out the IMF.
Say that I want to talk
about underwriting sterling.
Well, they want their pound of flesh
and they want you
to lay off the banks.
And you should issue an apology.
I'll talk to Rix.
He's in Davos.
Have you got that package?
I thought it was a
bit early for you.
Have you?
All right, don't panic.
Does that thing work?
Just do the coffee.
Is this a good place to be
if you're not drinking?
I'm drinking coffee...or I would be
if you'd hurry the fuck up.
Makes some people tetchy, Tony,
going on the wagon.
But you must be the exception.
Just go easy. That's all.
We're playing the long game.
You go easy too, this time.
With Rix.
Since we're handing out advice.
Your Wi-Fi's rubbish.
I preferred you when you were
drinking.
♪ ...And I caressed her, kissed her
♪ Told her I'd die before
I would let her out of my arms... ♪
♪ ..only 24 hours from Tulsa
♪ Only one day away from your arms
♪ I hate to do this to you... ♪
♪ ..I love somebody new
♪ What can I do... ♪
So the Iranian Foreign Secretary
might once have had an affair
with his wife's sister?
How's that going to help me?
I'm not suggesting you mention it.
And what will his secret service
be telling him about me?
That you're sleeping
with the Prime Minister's PPS?
That you rate your chances
very highly,
should Tom Dawkins self-destruct?
The chances of which
seem to be increasing by the hour.
Oh, that's clever.
That's very clever.
What you found?
I've found a battery...
..where no battery's
supposed to be.
Show this to your opposite number...
if an opportunity arises.
Who is it?
His name's Sami Sharour.
He was on the plane
with Charles Flyte.
And, er...
..he may have been working
for the Iranians.
Sir?What?
The biometric database
has been compromised.
And you're telling me why?
Because the subject
was Sami Sharour.
Apparently there
was a lack of clarity
over which assets
you wanted frozen.
The...knock-on effect impacted
on the tube company's systems.
Tom...
I'm, um...
Ros Yelland.
I know.
What's the arrangement?
Well, we...chat and...
Chat?
You whisper sweet nothings in her ear
about what I'm doing?
Get your phone out. Call her.
Tell her that I know...
and that you're saying goodbye.
Or you find someone else to work for.
So the waiter thinks, "Hang on,
"I won't give him back
the whole fiver.
"I'll give the three of them
?1 each."
So the three diners
have spent ?9 each, right?
Right.
Which is ?27, yeah?
The waiter pockets two, right?
Right.
So, that's 29. So, where's the other
pound gone? There was 30.
Michael, just discreetly stick this
laptop under the counter, would you?
You any good at maths?
Then he asked for a vodka martini,
which is pretty rare these days.
Looked a bit like, um...
What's his name?
I'm off.Oh, here...
Don't be leaving
your stamp album here again.
Philatelist!
Mr Foreign Minister,
good to meet you.
I wonder if you know who that is?
Should I?
We're all in.
Michael, the last time
that we met at Downing Street,
I was...
"Michael" or "Sir Michael"?
Sir Michael, of course. Jesus.
Sir Michael, the last time
that we met at Downing Street,
I was perhaps a little...
What?
Intemperate?
Intemperate. Perfect.
Yes, may the good Lord in his wisdom
preserve us from the intemperate.
Steel yourselves.
Tom, the Ros thing...
It's forgotten, Lee.
Have you lost interest
in this profile?
We were actually
just getting ready...
Sorry, Tom, I really need
to talk to you.
Does he know
something about you, Tom?
Because...
that's what I'm being told.
Do you know what this job is like?
It's like being under the knife
without anaesthetic, 24/7.
So give me your version.
There is no version.
I've... I've nothing to tell you.
This is your chance, Tom.
There is no story.
I can see it in your eyes.
There's nothing there.
Now, if you'll excuse me...
Do you think, Sir Michael,
that my intemperance
has contributed to the
destabilisation of the markets?
Vulture funds are almost
certainly playing
silly buggers in the CDS market.
The people of the United Kingdom have
poured 50 billion into your bank.
Do you think that merits any kind of
consideration of the public interest?
In an ideal world I'd agree,
but I'm afraid the bank
has only one duty.
To act in the shareholders'
interests.
Oh, good.
We represent 88% of them.
All the shareholders.
Politics is parochial,
Prime Minister. Finance is global.
Yes, but you're headquartered
in my jurisdiction.
Oh, we could up and go tomorrow.
You see, that's the kind
of remark that stokes
my intemperance, Sir Michael.
You invested 50 billion...
..and OK, granted, that buys you
some influence with my bank,
but what I'm saying is,
if you were to press that case,
we'd get very jittery.
And so would the rest of the banks.
And if we're jittery,
our share price falls.
And if our share price falls,
your 50 billion investment
goes down the toilet.
And any influence you might have had
over the bank goes with it.
So you're saying that we
have influence
so long as
we don't expect to use it?
If you like.
Ah, Mr Mukerjee.
Prime Minister.
Please, call me Tom.
Then it's Jitin.
I... I read your report.
Our two countries
have a long history together.
Yes, they do.
And a very amicable future,
I would have said.
Are we going to get
our hands dirty, Tom?
I've decided you're on my side.
Everyone else might have given up on
me, but I've still got, well...
..you.
So if I understand you right...
..you're wondering if this fella
here, Sami Sharour...
..was on the fatal flight
with our ex-Prime Minister.
And you're wondering...
..why he wasn't on the manifest.
And I presume you're also wondering
if he had something to do
with the plane going down.
So...
something you might not know...
There's a history of fundamentalism
in his family.
Apparently not him, though.
And he was...
He was arrested in 2011
for throwing a rock through
the window of a New York madrasah.
What the CIA would probably call...
.."links with radical Islam".
I'm only doing this for you.
You've come to hear me talk
on the mission's criteria,
but first, a few words from the
British Prime Minister, Tom Dawkins.
Good evening.
I'm hearing a lot about banks
upping sticks
and leaving the City of London,
no doubt to a financial centre
near you.
But before you welcome them with
open arms, I want you to remember
that it was the British people...
..who ploughed tens of billions
into these banks in 2008.
In return for this bailout,
they promised that they
would lend to small businesses.
Well, did they lend to small
businesses like they promised?
Excuse my French, but did they fuck!
'So...
'there's something in these photos
that you didn't see,
'clever as you are.
'I've decided you're on my side.
'Everyone else might have given up
on me, but I've still got, well...
'you.'
What you missed was the bottle.
First, it was in the baggage truck.
Then it wasn't.
And then it was.
So...
Did that harm it, did that damage
it, falling off like that?
What was in it?
Some of that drone fuel?
Why?
Any thoughts...
clever girl?
Who's there?
Ugh!
'He was arrested in 2011
'for throwing a rock through
the window of a New York madrasah.
'What the CIA would probably call...
'.."links with radical Islam". '
'I'm only doing this for you.'
And I've been told that
if I meddle in the affairs
of the Royal Caledonian Bank,
I'm going to jeopardise
the national shareholding.
But it seems to me that
the national shareholding
is valueless for the foreseeable
future,
so here's what I'm going to do.
I propose to buy up the remaining
shares and transform the bank
into an engine of prosperity...
..promoting business,
particularly small business,
and generate employment,
especially among young people.
Where's your phone, Tony?
An Englishman's home is his castle.
You can't just barge in.
Where is it?
What's going on
at the back of my head?
It's...
You've broken my fucking skull,
you animal... Ugh!
'Who's there?
'Ugh!'
'What did I ever do to you?'
Ugh!
Aagh...
Tell me where the phone is.
Agh!
Arrgh!
'No, no! No!'
Ughh!
Your phone.
Aargh!
Tony?
What's going on in there?
Are you all right?
Arrgh!
Shall I call the police?
I'm gonna call the police.
So, in the event that the pound
comes under further attack,
I have arranged with my friends
in the Indian government
to underwrite sterling.
And to the IMF I say,
sorry to disappoint,
but we won't be needing
you after all.
But in return for what?
That's a very good question.
Clever as you are, you know...
..if you've spotted it,
someone else has too.
So, the question is,
why don't they say
something about it?
I'll tell Tommy...like you wanted.
Huh?
We'll show him what we can do,
the two of us.
He's going to need
all the help you can get.
Are you listening?
Are you?
India has a 300-year supply of coal
and 400 million people
without electricity.
They need power, now, nationwide.
The United Kingdom
has two million people unemployed,
a world-leading role
in renewables technology,
and, as of today, a bank
dedicated to putting those people
and that technology to work.
The new Royal Caledonian Bank
will fund on a massive scale.
Yes, on a massive scale.
A joint British and Indian research,
development and production project
based in the United Kingdom
with the sole aim
of creating a renewable alternative
to the Indian reliance on coal.
At the same time,
the United Kingdom will withdraw
from all international agreements
coercing India
into fixed timetables
on climate change reduction
until they have achieved
national electrification.
He needs to know what we...found.
Tommy does.
I need to know you're listening.
Are you?
Clever girl.
What do you know?
Did you give it to him?
I can tell you what happened
to Tony, but I can't talk now.
There'll be someone monitoring
this phone.
You're suggesting he was an agent
of the Iranian government?
The press are digging. MI6, CIA.
Forget about the flight recorder.
Begins to look pretty compelling.
Prime Minister, you're in great
danger.
They've come for me.
Stop right there!
350 years of continuous trading
and shifting your fucking assests is
bringing my bank to its knees.
Tom served in
the British Army in Bosnia.
Might have been an idea to tell me
about the skeleton in your closet.
We can't sit on secrets like that.
This is misinformation.
This is bullshit.
Does everyone in this country want
a war with Iran?
Come into the Chamber now
and announce retaliation
or come in there and resign.
www.tvsubtitles.net